<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plain-dealing, and plain-meaning sermon, preach't in the parish church of St. Nicholas, Bristol, April. 6. 1660. Being the day appointed by the Parliament for publique fasting and humiliation for the sins of the nation, &amp;c. Together with a prefatory epistle, and subsequent vindication both of the sermon, and author. Wherein (besides an apology for home and plain-preaching) you have something offered to allay the heat of thier stomacks, and to temper the tongues of those, who (being ignorant in scripture) reproach and revile Presbytery and Presbyters. With some hints at Satans subtlety, and the mischief of those people, who brand zeal for God and truth (in free, home, and faithfull preaching) with the reproachful names of anger, passion, and railing.</title>
            <author>Farmer, Ralph.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85121</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F443</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1025_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208684</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867611</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867611</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119930</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85121)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119930)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 152:E1025[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plain-dealing, and plain-meaning sermon, preach't in the parish church of St. Nicholas, Bristol, April. 6. 1660. Being the day appointed by the Parliament for publique fasting and humiliation for the sins of the nation, &amp;c. Together with a prefatory epistle, and subsequent vindication both of the sermon, and author. Wherein (besides an apology for home and plain-preaching) you have something offered to allay the heat of thier stomacks, and to temper the tongues of those, who (being ignorant in scripture) reproach and revile Presbytery and Presbyters. With some hints at Satans subtlety, and the mischief of those people, who brand zeal for God and truth (in free, home, and faithfull preaching) with the reproachful names of anger, passion, and railing.</title>
                  <author>Farmer, Ralph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by S. Griffin, and are to be sold by Thomas Wall by the Tolezey in Cornstreet in Bristol,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The epistle dedicatory signed: Ra: Farmer.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 19.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religious tolerance --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119930:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119930:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Plain-dealing, and Plain-meaning SERMON, Preach't in the Pariſh Church of St. <hi>Nicholas, Briſtol,</hi> April 6. 1660. Being the day appointed by the Parliament for publique Faſting and Humiliation for the ſins of the NATION, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Together with a prefatory Epiſtle, and ſubſequent Vindication both of the Sermon, and Author. Wherein (beſides an Apology for home and plain-preaching) you have ſomething offered to allay the heat of their ſtomacks, and to temper the tongues of thoſe, who (being ignorant in Scripture) reproach and revile <hi>Presbytery</hi> and <hi>PRESBYTERS.</hi> With ſome hints at SATANS ſubtlety, and the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief of thoſe people, who brand Zeal for God and Truth (in free, home, and faithfull preaching) with the reproachful names of Anger, paſſion, and Railing.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Ezek 33.30.</bibl>
               <p>Alſo thou ſon of Man, the children of thy people ſtill are talking againſt thee by the walls, and in the doors of their houſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 35 11.</bibl>
               <p>Falſe witneſſes did riſe up: They laid to my charge things that I knew not.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Matth. 5.11.</bibl>
               <p>Bleſſed are ye when men ſhall revile you, and perſecute you, and ſhall ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y all manner of evill againſt you falſely for my names ſake. Rejoyce and be exceeding glad: for great is your reward in heaven; for ſo perſecuted they the Prophets which were before you.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>S. Griffin,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Thomas Wall</hi> by the Tolezey in Cornſtreet in <hi>Briſtol,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:119930:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119930:2"/>
            <head>To the ſtrenuous <hi>Aſſertor</hi> of his Countreys Rights, <hi>Will: Pryn</hi> Eſquire, a choſen Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the High Court of <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am now upon an <hi>Appeal</hi> to the <hi>World,</hi> but not to <hi>all</hi> the world; for <hi>all</hi> are not competent <hi>Judges.</hi> But in my judgment I take <hi>you</hi> for the fitteſt man in the <hi>world</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, whether I have ſpoken <hi>againſt the King, or his coming in,</hi> in this enſuing <hi>Sermon.</hi> You whom the late <hi>King</hi> honoured with the title of the <hi>Cato,</hi> (the impartial <hi>Cato</hi>) of <hi>this age:</hi> You whom nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>fear</hi> nor <hi>flattery,</hi> nor <hi>perſecution</hi> can by as from the <hi>truth:</hi> You who have <hi>militated</hi> more, and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd</hi> more in the <hi>Kings</hi> behalf by your <hi>pen,</hi> then many Regiments of <hi>ſouldiers</hi> by their <hi>pikes</hi> &amp; <hi>muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets;</hi> To you I appeal in <hi>this</hi> matter: were it mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> I durſt make you my <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mpire,</hi> for I know your ability <hi>that</hi> way; Witneſs that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Book of yours of <hi>the Perpetuity of a regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate mans eſtate.</hi> But my appeal to you <hi>now</hi> is upon matter of <hi>fact</hi> &amp; <hi>diſcretion,</hi> whether my diſcourſe were <hi>ſcandalous</hi> or <hi>unſeaſonable.</hi> Sir, you are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the <hi>Topicks</hi> and proper ſeats of <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119930:3"/> in all kinds, <hi>deliberative, demonſtrative, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſive.</hi> You can diſcern whether I have <hi>ſinn'd</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the law of the <hi>Preacher.</hi> Had you been in the <hi>Country,</hi> this <hi>Sermon</hi> had waited upon you for your <hi>Deleatur,</hi> or <hi>Imprimatur,</hi> before it had gone unto the <hi>Preſs:</hi> But mine and the Book-ſellers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions that your <hi>greater</hi> &amp; manifold occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (now that you are in <hi>London</hi>) would not offer us ſuch a time of <hi>leiſure</hi> w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> you, as to peruſe it <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand,</hi> hath with held me from <hi>that</hi> attempt. Yet I could not <hi>with-draw</hi> from my <hi>reſolutions</hi> to crave your juſt <hi>deciſion.</hi> If you find me <hi>guilty,</hi> ſtrike out your name, and <hi>diſown</hi> the <hi>dedication,</hi> which would be a <hi>ſorer blow</hi> to me, then <hi>all</hi> the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of my <hi>Calumniators:</hi> But if you find me <hi>inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi> then let my <hi>Sermon</hi> (with its <hi>Appendices</hi>) goe forth with your <hi>auſpicious</hi> tutelage. I have one thing to <hi>beg</hi> of you, and that is, <hi>That the good old Cauſe may not be forgotten.</hi> And I ſhall beg of <hi>God</hi> (whoſe cauſe it is) a bleſſing upon <hi>you,</hi> and upon the <hi>great Councel,</hi> whereof you are a choſen <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> that the Lord would make you <hi>repairers of our breaches, and reſtorers of our paths to dwell in.</hi> Theſe are the <hi>deſires</hi> and <hi>prayers</hi> of him who is</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Yours moſt ready to ſerve you in all Chriſtian Offices R.A: FARMER.</signed>
               <dateline>From my houſe in <hi>Briſtol.</hi> 
                  <date>April 30. 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119930:3"/>
            <head>A Prefatory Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <p>ITS not the <hi>leaſt</hi> part of our <hi>work</hi> who are <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the <hi>Word</hi> to ſuit our <hi>Texts</hi> and <hi>Subjects:</hi> And in <hi>both</hi> (in a <hi>good</hi> ſenſe) to obſerve that <hi>direction</hi> in Rom. 12.11. (as the Vulgar Latine reads it) to <hi>ſerve the time;</hi> That is, to ſuit our <hi>diſcourſes</hi> to the <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> to the occaſions, <hi>times,</hi> and <hi>perſons</hi> wherein we live, and <hi>to whom</hi> we are to preach. <hi>Solomon</hi> the wiſeſt Preacher that ever was (<hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the wiſdome of <hi>God</hi> himſelfe excepted) tells us, <hi>that words ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in ſeaſon</hi> (i. e. according to the time, occaſion and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the perſons ſpoken to) <hi>are like apples of gold in pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of ſilver,</hi> very <hi>good,</hi> very <hi>pleaſant.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 25.11.</note> And he alſo tells us that <hi>Preachers who are wiſe,</hi> and would teach their people true and ſaving knowledge, they muſt be heedful and carefull not to utter (as many pretended Enthuſiaſts do) <hi>quicquid in buccam venerit, but to ſeek out,</hi> compoſe, and to <hi>ſet in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> what they are to treat on:<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.9,10.</note> And to find out <hi>acceptable,</hi> delightful, taking, winning <hi>words</hi> and matter. In the Hebrew it is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>verba voluntatis,</hi> i. e. ſuch <hi>words</hi> and <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> as might <hi>captivate</hi> and take the <hi>wills</hi> and <hi>affections</hi> of their Auditors: And (as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> phraſes it)<note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.5.</note> 
               <hi>bring into captivity every thought to the obedience of Chriſt.</hi> And this I conceive (in great part) was that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that <hi>craft;</hi> ſubtlety, and <hi>cunning</hi> that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> (in preaching) uſed to <hi>catch the Corinthians.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.16.</note> 
               <hi>Being crafty, I caught you with guile.</hi> He carried himſelfe ſo both in <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> that he drew them <hi>on,</hi> and brought them <hi>over</hi> to that he <hi>deſired.</hi> In ſum he did what he told them elſewhere, <hi>He became all to all men, that he might ſave ſome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.22.</note> In the Greek the word [men] is not. In the Originall it runs thus; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I am <hi>made</hi> (or become) <hi>all</hi> to <hi>all.</hi> I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb facs="tcp:119930:4"/> my ſelfe to all <hi>times,</hi> and all <hi>perſons.</hi> I uſe all <hi>means</hi> to ſave ſome, in and by the exerciſe of my Miniſtery. And truly this hath <hi>alwayes</hi> been in my <hi>eye,</hi> and this way I have ever <hi>approv'd</hi> of; And to (my poor ability) <hi>followed</hi> in the courſe of my <hi>Miniſtery:</hi> having <hi>finiſhed</hi> a Text and Subject, it hath ſometimes put me to as carefull thoughts <hi>what</hi> to preach next, as <hi>how</hi> to preach: Eſpecially upon ſpeciall and <hi>extraordinary</hi> occaſions. I have been ſollicitous to take all <hi>advantages</hi> that might bring and <hi>win</hi> over thoſe I <hi>preach</hi> to, to the truth to be propoſed. And being invited to the obſervation of the laſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn <hi>Faſt,</hi> I accordingly made choiſe of the <hi>Text</hi> which was the ſubject of the <hi>Sermon</hi> following: How apt and <hi>pertinent,</hi> let <hi>wiſe men</hi> judge, I lookt with a ſad eye upon our <hi>manifold</hi> breaches, and our <hi>more</hi> ſins, (the <hi>cauſe</hi> of thoſe breaches.) And yet conſidering the Lords gracious <hi>diſpenſations</hi> (in the wonderfull and unexpected turns of providence) I was under ſome hopefull <hi>expectations</hi> that the Lord would alſo <hi>heale</hi> our <hi>breaches,</hi> if our wilfull obſtinacy and <hi>impenitence</hi> did not <hi>hinder</hi> and with-hold ſo great a <hi>mercy.</hi> And the people in <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall,</hi> and my ſelfe in <hi>particular,</hi> being in an apprehenſion and <hi>expectation</hi> of the <hi>Kings</hi> being brought unto the <hi>throne,</hi> I <hi>thence</hi> took occaſion in my diſcourſe to <hi>ſuggeſt</hi> ſuch things as I conceiv'd might be profitable and <hi>conducent</hi> to what I <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended,</hi> which was to <hi>in vite them to repentance.</hi> But as he ſaid of Bookes, <hi>Pro captu lectoris habent ſua fata libelli,</hi> According to the <hi>underſtanding</hi> of the <hi>Reader,</hi> ſo do <hi>books</hi> find <hi>entertainment:</hi> So may we ſay of <hi>Sermons;</hi> Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the underſtanding of our <hi>Auditors,</hi> ſo are our Sermons <hi>accepted</hi> or <hi>rejected.</hi> Nay not onely according to their <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> but many times (and with moſt) according to their <hi>ignorance,</hi> humours, fancies, <hi>intereſts.</hi> It was <hi>always</hi> ſo, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles:</hi> Some <hi>believed</hi> their prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and ſome <hi>mock'd</hi> and <hi>derided.</hi> Some <hi>reproacht,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied and ſlandered both <hi>them</hi> and their <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119930:4"/>
            <p>Thus it hath fared with <hi>me</hi> not onely at <hi>other</hi> times, but alſo at <hi>this</hi> time: And it is ſome comfort to me that I am not <hi>alone;</hi> But that my <hi>betters</hi> find no <hi>better</hi> entertainment from their <hi>Auditors,</hi> it makes me <hi>think</hi> it is not <hi>our</hi> fault, but <hi>theirs.</hi> And becauſe it doth ſo much <hi>quadrare</hi> (ſo ſuite) with <hi>my</hi> condition, I will make ſo <hi>bold,</hi> as to lay the complaint of a moſt <hi>eminent,</hi> able, and godly learned <hi>Preacher,</hi> (in his <hi>own</hi> words) before you, not being able to do it in <hi>better</hi> lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. It is the Reverend Dr. <hi>Gauden,</hi> in his <hi>Sermon</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church <hi>London,</hi> before the Lord <hi>Mayor,</hi> Lord <hi>Generall,</hi> &amp;c. Feb. 28. 1659. Being a day of Solemn <hi>Thankſgiving,</hi> &amp;c. Wherein (intending to deale <hi>faithfully</hi> and <hi>plainly,</hi> Having propoſed his <hi>Text,</hi> after a few words, he makes this <hi>entrance</hi> in page 2, 3, &amp; 4. of that <hi>Sermon</hi> to this <hi>purpoſe.</hi> He ſeems very apprehenſive of the <hi>danger</hi> and <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty</hi> of <hi>free</hi> preaching in <hi>theſe</hi> times, wherein (as he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) people are not onely <hi>impatient to be touched freely, and ſearched throughly,</hi> but are alſo <hi>prone to plead</hi> (as the Devills in the <hi>Goſpel</hi>) who had poſſeſſed the poor man now a <hi>long</hi> time) <hi>againſt all health and recovery.</hi> Many men being like <hi>Cantors</hi> and <hi>Lazors</hi> (Canting beggars) <hi>in love with their wounds and ulcers:</hi> As getting their living more eaſily by keeping them <hi>open,</hi> raw, and running, then if they ſhould <hi>quite</hi> heal them up. And he takes notice of the <hi>tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of many mens minds,</hi> who are onely for <hi>lenitives</hi> and <hi>oyles,</hi> for <hi>ſoft, ſmooth,</hi> &amp; ſupple <hi>applications</hi> even to their moſt <hi>deſperate</hi> hurts: But he profeſſes, <hi>to chuſe not to preach at all, then to preach timerouſly and precariouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as if he ſhould ask men leave to be honeſt, or were afraid to ſpeak the word of God to them.</hi> And he further ſayes; When he is called to ſpeak in <hi>Gods</hi> name, he muſt be <hi>Parrheſiaſtes</hi> as well as <hi>Eccleſiaſtes.</hi> I am (ſayes he) to do it as a <hi>work-man that needs not to be aſhamed,</hi> either for his <hi>ignorance,</hi> or <hi>cowardiſe,</hi> or <hi>indiſcretion.</hi> And whether
<pb facs="tcp:119930:5"/> men will <hi>hear,</hi> or <hi>forbear,</hi> the <hi>whole counſel of God muſt be delivered in its ſeaſon,</hi> ſo as becomes the words of <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berneſs and truth:</hi> For the Church and Pulpit muſt not be a ſanctuary for <hi>inſolency,</hi> nor a Burrow or retreat for <hi>rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> No, however men become our <hi>enemies</hi> for ſpeaking the <hi>truth,</hi> yet it's better <hi>ſo,</hi> then to have <hi>God</hi> our enemie for <hi>ſmothering</hi> it, when it is <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>ſeaſonable:</hi> And ſuch it is when <hi>neceſſary</hi> and ſoveraign to <hi>heale</hi> the hurt of a <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State.</hi> Thus that reverent perſon. And then <hi>complains,</hi> It hath been his <hi>fate frequently</hi> to <hi>offend</hi> ſome men, when he hath been moſt intent to <hi>ſerve</hi> them, by <hi>Texts</hi> and <hi>Sermons,</hi> which he thought moſt <hi>apt, uſeful, and innocent;</hi> And then gives in three <hi>Texts</hi> which he preacht upon on 3. ſeveral great and ſpecial occaſions. One before the <hi>King,</hi> another before the <hi>long Parliament,</hi> the third elſewhere. And of all three (ſays he) <hi>though wholſome and innocent Texts,</hi> and I hope ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cordingly handled; <hi>yet I heard ſome unpleaſing eccho's and reflexions.</hi> The ſore and <hi>itching</hi> eares of ſome men in <hi>all</hi> ages are ſuch, that they will not endure <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or <hi>ſound and wholſome doctrine,</hi> though the pain ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth from the <hi>ſores</hi> and inflammation in <hi>themſelves,</hi> and <hi>not from the plaiſter and hand which honeſtly applyes it.</hi> Yet they are prone, as in fell <hi>boyls</hi> and acute <hi>tumours,</hi> when but <hi>touched</hi> (though but <hi>gently</hi>) to <hi>fly</hi> upon thoſe that are <hi>next</hi> them, and cry aloud, <hi>O you hurt me,</hi> when the hurt is <hi>within,</hi> and from <hi>their ſelves,</hi> and their <hi>ſound parts will endure free and rough handling;</hi> ſuch as are <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found</hi> do moſt <hi>want</hi> it. And therefore <hi>if we will be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to God, to our own ſouls, and our hearers, we muſt not flatter their ſores to their ruine:</hi> but rather chooſe to <hi>heal</hi> them, though at <hi>preſent</hi> we be thought to <hi>hurt</hi> them. Nor (ſayes he farther) ſhall our labour <hi>of love</hi> be in <hi>vain,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the <hi>Lord,</hi> or before <hi>good men,</hi> who at length will find by <hi>experience</hi> that <hi>the wounds of a friend (which let out
<pb facs="tcp:119930:5"/> the putrified matter of painful tumors) are better then the kiſſes of an enemy, which do</hi> (infidis cicatricibus cuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culam obducere.) <hi>Skin over with unfaithful ſcars, the ill-ſearched, &amp; ill-purged Ulcers of mens hearts and lives.</hi> I hope this <hi>worthy</hi> perſon will <hi>pardon</hi> me, that I have made <hi>ſo bold</hi> with him, as to <hi>borrow</hi> ſo much <hi>from</hi> him, I ſhall pay it him in thoſe <hi>reſpects</hi> and honour I owe unto him for his <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> diſpoſition and temper. And I rather chuſe <hi>thus</hi> to do, as hoping his <hi>worth</hi> will add more <hi>weight,</hi> then if it had been delivered in my <hi>own</hi> words.</p>
            <p>And ſee, what is here delivered in the <hi>Sermon,</hi> was but as a <hi>propheſie</hi> what befell this good <hi>man</hi> and good <hi>Preacher</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards: For in his <hi>Epiſtle Dedicatory</hi> to the <hi>Lord May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, Aldermen,</hi> and Court of <hi>Common-Councel</hi> (who gave him <hi>thanks</hi> for his <hi>Sermon,</hi> and intreated him to <hi>print</hi> it) he tells them, he heard <hi>ſome more offended at the plain-dealing he uſed,</hi> which poſſibly (ſayes he) was from their <hi>over-rawneſs,</hi> and <hi>ſoreneſs,</hi> more then from my <hi>roughneſs.</hi> As I aym to do things <hi>faithfully, perſonally;</hi> ſo <hi>decently,</hi> and <hi>diſcreetly.</hi> Nor do I thinke I am to learn of thoſe <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious Cato's how to preach,</hi> any more then they will learn of me <hi>to buy and ſell,</hi> or how <hi>to fight and war.</hi> And he ſays, No man may <hi>wonder,</hi> if he dare to <hi>reprove</hi> thoſe ſins which ſome dare to <hi>do;</hi> or to <hi>approve,</hi> but dare not <hi>hear</hi> of, or <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.</hi> And that his parrheſia and freedome of ſpeech, as a <hi>man,</hi> a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and a <hi>Preacher,</hi> was ſuch, as became his feeling of the publique <hi>miſeries,</hi> the deſire of the Publique <hi>tranquility,</hi> and the ſenſe of that <hi>fidelity</hi> he did owe to <hi>God,</hi> his <hi>Countrey, them</hi> (to whom he preacht) <hi>and his owne ſoul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the <hi>Lord</hi> knows my owne <hi>ſoul</hi> can, and doth atteſt the <hi>ſame,</hi> in my poor weak labours and indeavours <hi>alſo;</hi> Though infinitely <hi>ſhort</hi> in <hi>worth</hi> of this moſt reverent perſon: To end with him, he tells us, <hi>Theſe are not times to palliate and
<pb facs="tcp:119930:6"/> ſpeak ſmooth and ſoft things: Never age had fouler hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, or tumours, more felt and more painfull; more hard, and leſs mollified:</hi> And ſayes; <hi>No, as he would not injure any man, or feſter the times: ſo he abhorr'd to flatter them; which is the greateſt injury a Preacher can do to Church and State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I muſt confeſs the ſubject of <hi>my</hi> diſcourſe was not of ſo <hi>high</hi> a nature, nor had I to do with ſo <hi>high</hi> an Auditory. Nor am I fit for ſuch an <hi>undertaking;</hi> nor have I quoted all this to any ſuch purpoſe.</p>
            <p>But to let our <hi>petty</hi> world (here at home) know, that <hi>plain, free, home,</hi> and (as this worthy Doctor phraſes it) <hi>perſonal</hi> preaching, is not ſuch a <hi>ſin</hi> as our <hi>Ignaro's</hi> would <hi>make</hi> it. And that though people be <hi>angry</hi> with us for <hi>ſuch</hi> preaching, we muſt not ceaſe to <hi>ſecure</hi> our conſcience in the <hi>faithfull</hi> (though <hi>unpleaſing</hi>) diſcharge of our <hi>duty:</hi> And good Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, know, That as a <hi>neceſſity</hi> is laid upon thoſe who are <hi>ſent</hi> to <hi>preach;</hi> So a neceſſity is likewiſe laid upon them to deale <hi>punctually</hi> and particularly with the <hi>perſonall ſinnes</hi> (I don't ſay naming the perſons) of thoſe they <hi>preach</hi> to; which if they do, they ſhall be ſure to <hi>heare</hi> on't, If not with perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the <hi>hand,</hi> yet with perſecution of the <hi>tongue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas ſome may ſay <hi>this,</hi> or <hi>that,</hi> in <hi>ſuch</hi> or <hi>ſuch</hi> a Sermon might have been <hi>forborn,</hi> Perhaps we may ſay ſo <hi>too.</hi> But if we (whom the <hi>Lord</hi> hath ſent to do his <hi>work;</hi> And (in our <hi>Studies</hi> applying our ſelves unto it) having <hi>beſought</hi> the Lord to teach us <hi>what</hi> to ſpeak, and <hi>how</hi> to ſpeak, as may be moſt for his <hi>glory,</hi> and the peoples <hi>good;</hi> And it be <hi>ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> to us, that <hi>ſuch,</hi> or <hi>ſuch</hi> expreſſions would be moſt <hi>taking;</hi> or beſt <hi>remembred:</hi> Our diſcourſe <hi>thus</hi> and <hi>thus</hi> clothed in <hi>language,</hi> would be moſt <hi>effectual</hi> and <hi>conducent</hi> to the end intended. If we are thus <hi>perſwaded</hi> in our <hi>Conſciences,</hi> How ſhall we <hi>refuſe</hi> it?</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>It may be 'twill</hi> offend, <hi>diſpleaſe ſome? They'l</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill <hi>at it?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119930:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It may be ſo; We hope <hi>not;</hi> We know <hi>no</hi> reaſon for it. Wee'l <hi>pray</hi> they may not. But is it a <hi>neceſſary truth?</hi> Is it <hi>uſefull,</hi> and <hi>ſeaſonable?</hi> Is <hi>good</hi> like to be done by it? (which is our <hi>errand</hi> and buſineſſe.) Muſt we <hi>forbear</hi> that which <hi>God</hi> in our Conſciences (according to his Word) tells us will do <hi>ſome</hi> people <hi>good,</hi> becauſe it will offend <hi>others?</hi> Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly friends we (<hi>Preachers</hi>) many times <hi>offend</hi> (yea <hi>hurt</hi>) o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, when we <hi>know</hi> it not, nor ever <hi>meant</hi> or <hi>intended</hi> it. But is it <hi>our</hi> fault, or <hi>theirs?</hi> We meane the whole Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>good.</hi> If any do not <hi>underſtand,</hi> or <hi>miſ-underſtand,</hi> or <hi>miſ-interpret,</hi> or <hi>pervert</hi> our words, or meaning, Is it <hi>our</hi> fault? I tell you Sirs, this <hi>great</hi> truth, and minde it; <hi>Much</hi> hurt (yea more <hi>hurt</hi> then <hi>good</hi>) is <hi>many</hi> times (nay <hi>moſt</hi> times) done by our <hi>Sermons.</hi> And we (Preachers) in that, <hi>not</hi> to be blamed, but are accepted of <hi>God</hi> therein, and ſhall be <hi>rewarded.</hi> It's a <hi>ſad</hi> word (too true to many) that <hi>we further their damnation by our preaching.</hi> That one place (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14,15,16. <hi>ver.</hi>) fully proves all this. And <hi>whence</hi> all this? But becauſe <hi>people</hi> do not <hi>heed</hi> (as they ought) what we ſay: Or they don't <hi>underſtand</hi> it, Or they won't <hi>practice</hi> it, Or (which is <hi>worſt</hi> of all) they <hi>withſtand, gainſay, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert,</hi> or <hi>wreſt</hi> it. And what? muſt we therefore <hi>forbear</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching? Muſt we <hi>forbear</hi> the <hi>truth,</hi> becauſe they <hi>abuſe</hi> it? And (perhaps) us <hi>for</hi> it? I trow <hi>not.</hi> And let me put <hi>another</hi> Caſe. It may be God by his <hi>Spirit</hi> (for we hope we are not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his <hi>imbreathings</hi> and <hi>ſuggeſtions</hi>) according to his word <hi>convinces</hi> and perſwades me, that <hi>ſuch</hi> or <hi>ſuch</hi> a truth (as before) is very <hi>ſeaſonable</hi> and <hi>uſefull:</hi> And in ſteps <hi>ſelfe,</hi> and <hi>tells</hi> me, This truth is teo <hi>tart,</hi> and it may create me <hi>trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> I may <hi>heare</hi> ill, and <hi>beare</hi> ill for <hi>ſpeaking</hi> it; What ſhall I do in <hi>this</hi> caſe? Why truly, <hi>Selfe</hi> is ſometimes to be <hi>hearkned</hi> to: For we are not to <hi>create</hi> to our ſelves trouble <hi>unneceſſarily.</hi> But (as before) it is a truth <hi>neceſſary</hi> and <hi>ſeaſonable;</hi> May I (for <hi>fear</hi>) <hi>forbear</hi> it? Will you read
<pb facs="tcp:119930:7"/> what one (no <hi>phanatick,</hi> or of a factious or <hi>turbulent</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit) ſayes, A man of <hi>great</hi> parts, learning, and judgement, Dr. <hi>Jackſon;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Jackſon</hi> heretofore Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of <hi>Corp: Chriſti</hi> Colledg in <hi>Oxford,</hi> In his Treatiſe of <hi>Juſtifying Faith,</hi> sect. 2. cap. 15. pag. 279</note> 
               <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>may deny Chriſt, or manifeſt their aſhamedneſs of his Goſpel as directly, by not laying his Law as cloſely to the great</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rods <hi>of the world</hi> (<hi>as</hi> John Baptiſt <hi>did</hi> (<hi>ſuppoſing the caſe to be as notorious, and as well known unto them</hi> (he meanes the Miniſters, as <hi>Herods</hi> was to <hi>John Baptiſt:</hi>) In this caſe they may as <hi>directly</hi> deny Chriſt, or be aſham'd of his <hi>Goſpel</hi> (in not dealing plainly and reproving) <hi>as if they had been afraid to confeſſe him, for feare of being put out of the Synagogue,</hi> &amp;c. And he ſays, <hi>were</hi> John Baptiſts <hi>kind of preaching uſed in many Kingdoms, though by ſuch as profeſſe the ſame Religion with the Potentates, whom they ſhould offend with their boldneſs, I think</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>it would prove matter of Martyrdome in the end.</hi> And he farther ſayes; <hi>In that any age ſince Chriſtian Religion was firſt propagated, hath wanted ſtore of Martyrs, 'tis more to be a tributed unto the negligence, ignorance, and hypocriſie, or want of courage in Chriſts Ambaſſadors, or appointed Paſtors, then unto the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, mildneſſe, or fidelity of the Flock, eſpecially of the Bel-weathers, or chief Ring-leaders.</hi> And now friend! sare we (Miniſters) thus in <hi>danger?</hi> what ſhall we <hi>do?</hi> Truly we have more need of your <hi>pitty,</hi> and your <hi>prayers,</hi> then your <hi>cenſures</hi> and <hi>reproaches.</hi> But <hi>jacta eſt alea,</hi> It's better <hi>obey</hi> God, and <hi>fear</hi> God then men, and <hi>pleaſe</hi> God then men, Or our <hi>ſelves</hi> either; for in ſo doing, we ſhall have <hi>peace</hi> with <hi>him,</hi> and in our <hi>own</hi> conſciences, which is better then all the <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>comforts</hi> the world can <hi>afford</hi> us. And therefore we will bear it <hi>patiently, comfortably.</hi> But yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Sathan</hi> makes no ſmall <hi>advantage</hi> of thoſe <hi>reproaches</hi> that are caſt upon the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Goſpel (of which farther in the <hi>vindication</hi>) I ſhall once more <hi>appear</hi> in <hi>Print</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119930:7"/> (though much aginſt my purpoſe) to ſtop the <hi>mouth</hi> either of <hi>prejudice,</hi> or wilfull <hi>calumny,</hi> or <hi>ſottiſh</hi> and <hi>ſleepy igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> or <hi>byaſt</hi> intereſt, which will <hi>pervert</hi> any thing, be it never ſo <hi>innocent</hi> and <hi>harmleſſe.</hi> And this not without the advice and counſell of ſome worthy <hi>friends,</hi> and well-wiſhers who have been very ſenſible of thoſe <hi>unworthy</hi> rumours that have bin <hi>raiſed</hi> &amp; <hi>ſpread</hi> by occaſion of this enſuing <hi>Sermon,</hi> which I ſhall now (good <hi>Reader</hi>) lay before thee, according to mine owne <hi>notes,</hi> and the beſt I could get of thoſe who <hi>noted</hi> after me. Poſſibly this trouble might be brought upon me, that ſome may reap benefit by this <hi>Sermon</hi> (or appendant diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) <hi>printed,</hi> as I have <hi>ſome</hi> cauſe to hope <hi>ſome</hi> did, when it was <hi>preached.</hi> To which end I commend thee and it unto <hi>God,</hi> beſeeching him to beſtow upon <hi>thee</hi> and <hi>me the ſpirit of power, of love, and of a ſound minde,</hi> 2 Tim. 1.7. For which thy prayers are deſired at the Throne of Grace (if thou haſt any intereſt there) by him, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy faithful friend and wel-wiſher, RA: FARMER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF thou be one of the <hi>ſimple</hi> ones, let me adviſe thee: <hi>Shoot not thy bolt too ſuddenly,</hi> but receive <hi>information</hi> from thoſe who are <hi>wiſer.</hi> If thou be a perſon of <hi>judgement</hi> and <hi>diſcretion,</hi> make <hi>uſe</hi> of it, and do not read by <hi>ſnatches,</hi> and then <hi>cenſure,</hi> but read <hi>all.</hi> And where thou poſſibly mayſt <hi>ſtumble</hi> or <hi>doubt</hi> (having read the former <hi>Epiſtle</hi>) favour me ſo <hi>far,</hi> as to <hi>read</hi> alſo my <hi>Vindication</hi> after. And I ſuppoſe we ſhall part <hi>friends,</hi> notwithſtanding all evill <hi>ſurmiſings.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>Farewel.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:119930:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119930:8"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>HOSEA 6.1.</bibl>
                  <p>Come let us return unto the Lord, for he hath torn, and he will heal us; he hath ſmitten, and he will binde us up.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee have here a <hi>repenting</hi> people; and they the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Gods people. Now repenting <hi>ſuppoſes</hi> ſinning; for repentance is <hi>not</hi> but for ſin. If there were no <hi>ſinning,</hi> there were no need of <hi>repenting.</hi> Now, <hi>All</hi> ſin, for <hi>there is no man living that ſinneth not,</hi> as 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.46. <hi>Particular</hi> perſons ſin, and <hi>people</hi> and <hi>Nations</hi> in general ſin. <hi>All</hi> ſin, even <hi>Gods</hi> people, his <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar</hi> people ſin. And if his people <hi>ſinne</hi> as well as others, they ſhall <hi>ſuffer</hi> as well as others: Nay, <hi>Becauſe</hi> they are <hi>his</hi> people, therefore, <hi>if they</hi> ſin, they <hi>above</hi> all others ſhall <hi>ſuffer.</hi> Thus the Lord by the Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> Chap. 3. verſ. 2. <hi>You onely have I known of all the families of the earth, therefore I will puniſh you for all your iniquities.</hi> Well, Gods people <hi>ſin,</hi> and Gods people <hi>ſuffer</hi> for their <hi>ſin:</hi> ſo theſe <hi>here.</hi> We may read of their ſin both <hi>before,</hi> and <hi>after</hi> the Text. In the Chapter <hi>before</hi> the Text, there you may read of <hi>multiplyed,</hi> complicated ſins, <hi>impudently, wilfully</hi> committed. Both <hi>Princes,</hi> the houſe of the <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> the people they had been <hi>nets</hi> and <hi>ſnares</hi> to betray one another into <hi>ſinne,</hi> Verſ. 1. of the foregoing Chapter. And in the 2d. Verſ. <hi>Thoſe revolters were profound to make ſlaughter;</hi> ſlaughter of <hi>men,</hi> and ſlaughter of <hi>ſacrifices.</hi> They would <hi>kill,</hi> and commit <hi>murder,</hi> and yet pretend unto <hi>Religion.</hi> And in this they were <hi>profound</hi> notable <hi>hypocrites,</hi> deep <hi>diſſemblers.</hi> For though <hi>they won't frame their courſes to Gods minde,</hi> verſ. 4. Yet <hi>they will go with their herds and their flocks to ſeeke the Lord,</hi> verſ. 6. Oh! they'l be <hi>hugely</hi> religious, they'l not ſpare for <hi>coſt,</hi> they brought their <hi>herds</hi> and their <hi>flocks</hi> to make <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices:</hi> But yet for all that, <hi>they ſhall not finde the Lord,</hi> ver. 6. God won't accept of ſuch <hi>impoſtors,</hi> ſuch <hi>pretenders,</hi> he hath <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn himſelf from them.</hi> He will not <hi>countenance, protect,</hi> or <hi>ſecure</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119930:9"/> them, in the ſame verſe. Nay, if they <hi>go on</hi> in their ſin, and go <hi>fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> from God, God will go yet <hi>farther</hi> from them; <hi>I will go and return to my place,</hi> ver. the laſt. God will not <hi>appear</hi> amongſt them as he was <hi>wont</hi> by his <hi>wonted</hi> mercies, and <hi>gracious</hi> providences; Let the <hi>Aſſyrian,</hi> and <hi>King Jareb</hi> help them if they can. Thoſe <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians of no value,</hi> to whom they fled for refuge and for <hi>healing,</hi> when they were ſmitten and wounded. If they <hi>ſerve</hi> falſe gods, let them when they have <hi>need</hi> go to <hi>them</hi> whom they have <hi>ſerved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was the ſtate and condition of the <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> at that time: But how was it with <hi>Ephraim?</hi> how was it with the <hi>people?</hi> (for ſo doth <hi>Ephraim</hi> ſometimes ſignifie.) Why, like <hi>Princes, like people.</hi> Being <hi>broken in judgement,</hi> (a ſottiſh, baſe, cowardly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany) <hi>they willingly walked after the Commandement.</hi> An <hi>Idolatrons</hi> command went forth from curſed <hi>Jeroboam:</hi> And the <hi>people</hi> being oppreſſed and over-born by power, they <hi>willingly walked after the commandement, verſ.</hi> 11. <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> makes men <hi>baſe</hi> and <hi>cowardly;</hi> and like <hi>Iſſachars Aſſe</hi> to couch and lie down under <hi>every</hi> burthen. And thus by their <hi>joynt</hi> and <hi>generall</hi> ſinning, they draw down a <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall</hi> judgement: And that is verified, <hi>Delirant Reges, plectuntur Achivi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now God being <hi>gone,</hi> all their <hi>ſhifting</hi> cannot help them. <hi>In vain is ſalvation hoped for from the hills, and from the multitude of mountains, Jer.</hi> 3.23. <hi>Great men,</hi> men in high places, men in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that are as <hi>mountains</hi> and <hi>hills,</hi> theſe cannot ſave <hi>Truly in the Lord God onely is the ſalvation of Iſrael,</hi> In the ſame vers.</p>
            <p>True, <hi>Salvation</hi> is in the <hi>Lord,</hi> but he is <hi>with-drawn</hi> and gone; he is <hi>returned to his place,</hi> and hides himſelfe, he <hi>will not</hi> ſave, we cannot <hi>finde</hi> him. Oh! fooliſh people and unwife, thus to <hi>forſake</hi> God, and to cauſe him to <hi>forſake</hi> you, and to leave you <hi>naked</hi> to your oppreſſors, when there is <hi>none</hi> to helpe, <hi>none</hi> to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
            <p>But <hi>is he clean gone? will the Lord caſt off for ever? will he be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable no more? hath God forgotten to be gracious? hath he in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſhut up his tender mercies? Pſal.</hi> 77.7. No, though Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>forget</hi> him, yet he will not <hi>forget</hi> them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.15. But if he will not <hi>forget</hi> them, why doth he <hi>with-draw?</hi> why doth he <hi>hide</hi> himſelfe? why doth he not come in for his peoples <hi>reſcue,</hi> their aid, their help and ſuccour? And how <hi>long</hi> will he hide himſelfe in this our affliction, diſtreſſe, and miſery? Why? he is <hi>with-drawn, and returned to his place,</hi> he hides himſelfe as it were in heaven, <hi>till we
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119930:9"/> acknowledge our offences,</hi> and by true repentance and unfained faith <hi>ſeek his face</hi> and favour; God doth <hi>with-draw</hi> to this purpoſe, that by his <hi>with-drawing</hi> he might <hi>draw</hi> us after him. He hides himſelfe till we <hi>acknowledge our offences,</hi> and by a lively act of faith <hi>fervently</hi> ſeek his face. For <hi>ſurely</hi> (ſaith the Lord, if they be not altogether ſenceleſs) <hi>in their affliction they will ſeeke me early,</hi> dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, ſeriouſly, <hi>Chap.</hi> laſt, <hi>verſ.</hi> laſt. <hi>Come therefore, and let us return unto the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. Come let <hi>us, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> that are <hi>here</hi> this day, Come let <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s:</hi> And oh! that <hi>all</hi> the Nation might hear this Call, and <hi>anſwer</hi> it: <hi>Come let us return unto the Lord, for he hath torne and he will heal us, he hath ſmitten, and he will binde us up. After two dayes he will revive us. In the third day he will raiſe us up, and we ſhall live in his ſight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have in the words,
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, an <hi>invitation</hi> to repentance.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, an <hi>incouragement</hi> thereunto.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>The <hi>invitation, Come let us return unto the Lord.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>incouragement, He hath torn, and he will heale us; he hath ſmitten, and he will binde us up.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Text may be taken as the Word of God, by the <hi>Prophet,</hi> put into the peoples <hi>mouths;</hi> Or as a <hi>direction</hi> and <hi>preſcription</hi> from God to his people, ſhewing them <hi>what to do</hi> in a ſad afflicted ſtate and condition. And beloved, this is no <hi>ſtrange</hi> notion, And it is a <hi>comforting</hi> and encouraging conſideration: God, he is ſo <hi>willing</hi> of his peoples <hi>returnings,</hi> that they might enjoy his favourable coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, as that, even when his afflicting hand is upon them, he not onely <hi>nvites</hi> them to it, but he even <hi>teaches</hi> them what to ſay, and in what <hi>words</hi> to addreſs themſelves unto him, that they might <hi>prevail</hi> with him; ſo gracious and <hi>tender</hi> a Father is he. This you have moſt ſweetly and fully in this very Prophet, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 14.1. <hi>O Iſrael return unto the Lord thy God, for thou haſt faln by thine iniquity, take with you words;</hi> (what are they? why thoſe that follow) <hi>ſay unto him, Take away our iniquities, and receive us graciouſly, and ſo will we render the calves of our lips.</hi> (And then it follows) <hi>Aſhur ſhall not ſave us,</hi> &amp;c. And when his people take this advice, and <hi>returne</hi> unto the Lord, then will the Lord <hi>heale their back-ſliding, and love them freely, then will his anger be turned away from them,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Oh beloved! what precious mercies, and unexpreſſible <hi>kindneſſes</hi> doth God offer to a <hi>repenting,</hi> a <hi>returning</hi> people: So tender a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is he, that he doth not only <hi>invite</hi> to repent, but teaches
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119930:10"/> them how to <hi>demean</hi> themſelves, and <hi>puts</hi> words into their mouths, to come unto him withal. As a tender <hi>Mother,</hi> that deſires to have her Child to go, ſtretches forth her hand to it, bids it <hi>come,</hi> gives words of <hi>encouragement</hi> to it that ſo it <hi>may</hi> come; Even ſo, God the Lord <hi>calls, invites,</hi> incourages his people to <hi>come</hi> unto him by unfeined repentance. Nay, not only ſo, but (as I ſaid) he <hi>teaches</hi> them with what words to come unto him. So here; <hi>Come let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. Beloved, it is a great incouragement to poor, diſtreſſed, afflicted ſouls, that the Lord is ſo <hi>deſirous</hi> of our <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> as that he not onely <hi>invites</hi> us to repent, but alſo <hi>tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches us how</hi> to repent, and return to him. <hi>Come therefore let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto the Lord. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> of this Land and Nation, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> of the three Nations, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> of this City, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> of this Congregation, <hi>Let us return unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Return unto the Lord!</hi> Why? have we <hi>departed</hi> from him? or <hi>can</hi> we depart from him? how can we depart from him? Is not God preſent <hi>every</hi> where? Pray ſirs read what <hi>David</hi> tells you in <hi>Pſ.</hi> 139.7. <hi>Whither ſhall I goe from thy ſpirit? or whither ſhall I flye from thy preſence? If I aſcend up into heaven, thou art there: If I take the wings of the morning, and dwell in the utmoſt parts of the ſea, even there ſhall thine hand lead me, and thy right hand ſuſtain me,</hi> How then can we <hi>go from</hi> God? and conſequently <hi>return to</hi> him?</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer: It is one thing to depart from (and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to return to) Gods <hi>eſſentiall</hi> and all-powerful preſence; And it is another thing to depart from, and return to his <hi>gracious</hi> and moſt <hi>merciful</hi> preſence. There is an <hi>eſſential</hi> preſence (a preſence of Gods <hi>power</hi> &amp; might,) And there is a <hi>gracious</hi> preſence; a preſence of his <hi>mercy</hi> and <hi>protection.</hi> Now, Gods <hi>eſſential</hi> preſence is never with-drawn from his Creatures; <hi>For in him they live, and move, and have their being.</hi> But then all who partake of his <hi>powerful</hi> preſence, do not partake of his <hi>gracious</hi> preſence. God is ſaid to be <hi>near</hi> or <hi>far</hi> off a people, and they are ſaid to be <hi>near</hi> or <hi>far</hi> from God, as they are in his <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>favour.</hi> When in mercy he extends his grace and <hi>favour</hi> to a people, then is he ſaid to be <hi>neare:</hi> unto them.</p>
            <p>Now beloved, There is <hi>one</hi> thing makes a diſtance and ſeparation between <hi>God</hi> and a <hi>ſoule,</hi> or between <hi>God</hi> and a <hi>people:</hi> and that is <hi>ſin,</hi> Iſa. 59.1. <hi>Behold the Lords hand is not ſhortned that he cannot ſave, neither his eare heavy that he cannot hear; but your iniquities have ſeparated between you and your God: Your ſins have hid his face
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119930:10"/> from you that he will not hear.</hi> By ſin we go <hi>away</hi> from God, and then God goes <hi>away</hi> from us: not by his <hi>power,</hi> that he cannot do, for he is preſent <hi>ſo</hi> every where, But he goes away, in with-drawing his <hi>grace,</hi> his <hi>love</hi> and <hi>favour,</hi> his moſt <hi>mercifull</hi> provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, protections, and <hi>ſpeciall</hi> preſervations from a people; <hi>That's</hi> Gods going away. And we by <hi>further</hi> ſin, go away <hi>further</hi> from God, and make the diſtance <hi>greater.</hi> And as by <hi>ſin</hi> we go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, ſo by <hi>repentance</hi> we return again to God, and ſo God <hi>returns</hi> again to us, and receives us into grace and favour.</p>
            <p>And now, ſirs, Let me aske you; Have we not ſinned, and gone away from God? Do not our iniquities teſtifie againſt us plainly, to our faces? And hath not God departed from us, and left us to run unto the <hi>Aſſyrian,</hi> and <hi>King Jareb?</hi> Interpreters do give vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Interpretations of that word what is meant by King <hi>Jareb;</hi> but yet all agree in this, that it ſignifies <hi>vaine</hi> helps. Friends, all helps and refuges are <hi>vaine,</hi> when God forſakes a people: And by the vanity and inſufficiency of all our helps and helpers that have all <hi>failed</hi> us, is it not very manifeſt that God hath hitherto <hi>left</hi> us? And why is it? but becauſe by ſin we have <hi>left</hi> him, and departed from <hi>him.</hi> Will you give me leave to be plain, (and why ſhould not I at ſuch a time as this is?) Have not our <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> heretofore, and our <hi>princely Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> been as <hi>ſnares upon Mizpah,</hi> and <hi>nets upon Tabor?</hi> (their high places and great offices) have they not <hi>tyrannized</hi> too much? Have they not <hi>revolted,</hi> and been <hi>profound</hi> to make ſlaughter, notwithſtanding they have been reproved and admoniſhed? I beſeech you ſirs, let not the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of our preſent <hi>greater</hi> ſufferings cauſe us altogether to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get our <hi>former</hi> iniquities. People are apt generally to complain of the preſent burthen, and murmur and forget what is <hi>paſt.</hi> And indeed, the <hi>greatneſſe</hi> of our burthens may make us willing to be <hi>rid</hi> of them; But yet let us not be ſuch ſottiſh aſſes, as not to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber our <hi>former</hi> gal'd backs. In this day of our Humiliation, when we are ſeeking for <hi>establiſhment,</hi> let us not forget the cauſe and ground of our <hi>unſettlement.</hi> It was a ſore Judgement that we were removed from our <hi>old</hi> foundations, but we muſt remember <hi>who</hi> it was that removed us. Friends let us conſider <hi>who</hi> it was that <hi>broke</hi> us, was it not the <hi>Lord? Come let us return unto the Lord, for he hath ſmitten us,</hi> &amp;c. Whatſoever be the <hi>hand</hi> that gives the ſtroke, or whoſoever be the <hi>inſtruments,</hi> yet it is <hi>God</hi> that guides it. <hi>Amos</hi> 3.6. <hi>Shall there be evill in the City, and the Lord hath not done it?</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119930:11"/> Shall there be evill in a <hi>City,</hi> in a <hi>Nation,</hi> in the <hi>three</hi> Nations, and the <hi>Lord hath not done it?</hi> By <hi>evil,</hi> I underſtand the evil of <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</hi> Now I ſay, is the evill of <hi>puniſhment</hi> in the Nation, in the <hi>three</hi> Nations, or upon any <hi>particular perſon,</hi> without the evill of <hi>ſin?</hi> will you ſay that the <hi>righteous Judge of heaven and earth</hi> hath not done right? When he hath brought the evill of <hi>puniſhment</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Nation or perſon, will you ſay that the evill of <hi>ſinne</hi> was not the preceding, and the procuring <hi>cauſe?</hi> I know well that God doth ſometimes puniſh the ſinne of <hi>Princes</hi> in and upon the <hi>People,</hi> and the ſin of <hi>People</hi> in and upon the <hi>Princes:</hi> but then <hi>both</hi> of them have <hi>ſinned.</hi> And though it may be the ſin of the <hi>one</hi> hath been more <hi>provoking</hi> then the ſinne of the <hi>other;</hi> yet when God comes with <hi>ſweeping judgements</hi> upon <hi>all,</hi> ſurely <hi>all have had a great ſhare in ſinning.</hi> And whether the ſins of our <hi>Princes,</hi> or the ſins of the <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> have brought theſe heavy judgements upon us, God the <hi>Judge</hi> of all the earth beſt knows: I ſhall not take upon me to <hi>determine</hi> it; for what am I, that I ſhould ſtep into the Chair of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? but yet let it be conſidered, From that very time that thoſe <hi>three eminent</hi> men ſtood in ſuch a diſgraceful and opprobrious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner upon a <hi>pillory</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> like Rogues and Cutpurſes, Let me tell you, ſince <hi>that</hi> time, neither the <hi>King, nor his party proſpered;</hi> I mean thoſe three worthy <hi>profeſſors</hi> of the three noble Sciences, <hi>Divinity, Law,</hi> and <hi>Phyſicke.</hi> But yet ſurely the ſins of this Land were ripe for judgement, or elſe the judgement would not have been ſo <hi>univerſal</hi> and generall. Hath not that dreadful judgement threatned and denounced of old, been moſt ſadly fulfilled upon us? <hi>Iſa. Ch.</hi> 3. begin. <hi>Behold, the Lord of hoſts doth take away from Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem and from Judah the ſtay and the ſtaff, the whole ſtay of bread and the whole ſtay of water: the mighty man and the man of war, the Judge and the Prophet, and the prudent, and the ancient, the Captain of fifties, and the honourable man, and the Counſellors, the cunning Artificer, and the eloquent Oratour: And I will give children to be your princes, and babes ſhall rule over them: And the people ſhall be oppreſſed every one by another, the child ſhall be have himſelfe proudly againſt the ancient, and the baſe againſt the honourable,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Hath not this been, and is it not <hi>this</hi> day ſadly verified? Is not contempt of <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> and <hi>Miniſtry</hi> grown to an <hi>inſupportable</hi> height? Hath not this I ſay, been ſadly verified in theſe our dayes? And is it not becauſe our <hi>ſins</hi> have been <hi>univerſall?</hi> We will not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the fault upon <hi>one</hi> head, but take it upon <hi>all,</hi> for we have <hi>all</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119930:11"/> contributed to the common heaps of <hi>ſin,</hi> and its infinite mercy that we have not been involved <hi>all</hi> in the common <hi>deſtruction:</hi> And have not <hi>we,</hi> we of this <hi>City,</hi> Magiſtrates and Miniſters, Parents and Children, Maſters and Servants, have we not <hi>all</hi> had a hand in the provocation more or leſſe? Can we forget that torpor, <hi>indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency,</hi> lukewarmneſſe and <hi>neutrality</hi> in our Magiſtracy, that hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore gave occaſion to that flood of <hi>Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> to come in amongſt us, and to make their <hi>ſeat</hi> here, to the <hi>poyſoning</hi> of the Country round about us?</p>
            <p>And as for the people of this City, let me not be <hi>unfaithfull</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them. Sirs, you complain that your Trade is <hi>decayed,</hi> and that you are ready to <hi>break,</hi> many of you, and I think you don't lie. Your Trade hath ſo <hi>forſaken</hi> you, that you are ready to <hi>forſake</hi> your Trades. And what is the reaſon? Surely God doth not leave a people but upon ſome occaſion. Truly when <hi>God</hi> forſakes <hi>Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> no marvail if <hi>they</hi> forſake their <hi>Trades;</hi> without God none can proſper: Tradeſmen may work hard, and fare hard, and go mean in habit, <hi>riſe up early, go to bed late,</hi> and cark and care, and get nothing unleſſe the <hi>Lord</hi> be with them. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſſe the Lord keep the City, the watchman watcheth in vain,</hi> &amp;c. Pſal. 127. Why now, a <hi>general forſaking</hi> of God, will cauſe the Lord to depart <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally from you.</hi> And beloved, that I may not dwell altogether on <hi>generals,</hi> not to mention that drunkenneſſe and prophaneneſſe, Sabboth-breaking, blaſphemous <hi>Oaths,</hi> and bitter <hi>Execrations, Pride,</hi> contempt of <hi>Magiſtracy,</hi> and undervaluing of our <hi>Superiours,</hi> which upon this loſſe of government is now ſadly <hi>returning</hi> again upon us, I ſay to let theſe alone (which yet do too evidently ſtare us in the face) and not to ſpeak to them: Do not the people of this <hi>City</hi> in general, &amp; have they not for <hi>a long time</hi> departed from God, and forſaken him in his <hi>Miniſters</hi> and ſervants whom he calls and ſends forth into his <hi>Vineyard?</hi> I will not now enter upon that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon place of that <hi>comfortable</hi> and <hi>honourable incouragement</hi> that is due to the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Goſpel: It's ſo clear a truth, that in plain reaſon you cannot gainſay it. And yet how <hi>infamouſly</hi> famous is this City <hi>above all other</hi> Cities in this Nation in <hi>this</hi> particular? Beloved, let me not be counted your Enemie for telling you the <hi>truth,</hi> (as you know I do) and dealing thus plainly; Surely ſirs, 'tis forſaking <hi>God,</hi> to forſake his <hi>ſervants,</hi> and he will not take it kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. I might mention other ſins whereby we have gone away from <hi>God,</hi> and ſo cauſed <hi>him</hi> to go away and forſake <hi>us.</hi> And if <hi>God</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119930:12"/> forſake us, no marvail if we be in a <hi>broken</hi> and diſtracted condition. See this 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.1,2,3. <hi>The ſpirit of the Lord came upon A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zariah the ſon of Obed, and he went to meet Aſa, and ſaid unto him, heare me Aſa, and all Judah and Benjamin, the Lord is with you whilſt you be with him: If you ſeek him he will be found of you, but if ye forſake him, he will forſake you.</hi> And ſee then their ſad ſtate after. Beloved, when God goes away with the <hi>honey</hi> of pity and mercy, he leaves ſuch a <hi>ſting</hi> of wrath and judgement behind him, that it ſhall vex and torment the very <hi>ſoules</hi> of a people: And then ſhall they finde that <hi>it is a ſad and a bitter thing to forſake the Lord</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now beloved, what remains, but that we having <hi>forſaken</hi> the Lord, we <hi>return again</hi> unto him. <hi>Come, let us return again unto the Lord, for he hath ſmitten, and he will heale,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Come let us <hi>return. Returning</hi> is nothing but <hi>repenting,</hi> and both of them do intend <hi>amendment. He that amends, repents,</hi> and he that repents <hi>returns;</hi> you ſhall find them oft put together in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. So <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.6. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, repent and turne your ſelves from your idols, and turne away your faces from all your abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations.</hi> So in Chap. 18. of the ſame Propheſie, <hi>Caſt away from you all your tranſgreſſions whereby you have tranſgreſſed, make you a new heart and a new ſpirit, for why will you dye O houſe of Iſrael?</hi> If you repent of the evill of <hi>ſin,</hi> God will repent of the evill of <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment:</hi> And if you return <hi>from</hi> your evill wayes, God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn <hi>to</hi> you in mercy, and tender compaſſion. <hi>Come then let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</hi> Return, return, <hi>O England,</hi> Return O <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> Return O thou <hi>my ſoule,</hi> and <hi>all you</hi> beloved that hear me this day, <hi>Return unto the LORD our God, for we are broken by our ſinne,</hi> Chap. 14 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Watchman what of the night?</hi> ſaith the Lord by the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 21.11,12. <hi>Watchman what of the night? He anſwered, the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cometh and alſo the night, if ye will enquire, enquire; Return, Come.</hi> Sirs, there is a night and a morning, this I ſee. If you put this Querie to me, <hi>Watchman what ſeeſt thou?</hi> I ſay the <hi>morning</hi> cometh, and alſo the <hi>night.</hi> We have a night and a morning in our Text, and ſo alſo in our Nation if we neglect it not. We have had by Gods <hi>chaſtiſing</hi> hand upon us (and oh, that it may be a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming</hi> hand) nights of <hi>tearing</hi> and <hi>ſmiting,</hi> the Lord hath <hi>torne</hi> us, and he hath <hi>ſmitten</hi> us. The hand of God upon us hath been a <hi>darke night</hi> of terrours and ſorrows. Dark and black diſpenſations hath the Lord exerciſed us with: He hath <hi>ſmitten</hi> us, he hath <hi>broken</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:119930:12"/> us, theſe are our <hi>nights.</hi> The <hi>morning</hi> now we hope alſo <hi>cometh:</hi> He will <hi>heale</hi> us, he will <hi>binde</hi> us up, that's the <hi>morning:</hi> And oh! <hi>Let that happy morning of</hi> Englands <hi>joy and deliverance make haſt, and not tarry.</hi> It may be, beloved, as we have been under the <hi>curſe,</hi> and judgement formerly mentioned, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3. So we may alſo ſee that happy <hi>morning</hi> of joy and reviving that is promiſed by the ſame Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> 1.25,26. <hi>I will turn my hand upon thee, and purely purge away thy droſſe, and take away all thy tinne.</hi> Do you expect a ſettlement? Truly then your <hi>ſins</hi> muſt be <hi>purged</hi> away, and then <hi>I will reſtore thy Judges as at the firſt, and thy Counſellors as at the beginning; Afterwards thou ſhalt be called a City of righteouſneſſe, the faithfull City: Sion ſhall be redeemed with judgement, and her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts with righteouſneſſe.</hi> Oh beloved! for ſuch a happy day, when God the Lord ſhall delight <hi>in</hi> us, and in mercy ſhall beſtow <hi>upon</hi> us that bleſſing here promiſed, of <hi>a righteous, juſt, and lawfull Government.</hi> And though God ſhould not do it in ſuch a way as we <hi>expect,</hi> yet he will do it in ſuch a way as is <hi>beſt</hi> for us, if we pleaſe him, which let us leave to him and our Superiours. <hi>Let us then return unto the Lord,</hi> and leave it to him for our eſtabliſhment and ſettlement. <hi>Let us</hi> I ſay, <hi>turn unto the Lord.</hi> Truly ſirs (will you give me leave to open my heart unto you) my heart trembles to think of ſome mens <hi>turnings,</hi> and of ſome <hi>turnings</hi> which <hi>ſome</hi> men look for; not a turning <hi>to</hi> God, but a turning further <hi>from</hi> God. Many people expect a <hi>change,</hi> not that they might change their <hi>lives,</hi> or <hi>manners;</hi> No, beloved, they would have a <hi>turning,</hi> not to <hi>God,</hi> but to the <hi>Devill.</hi> Oh! how would ſome men turn to the Devil of <hi>drunkenneſs?</hi> how would ſome men turn to the Devil of <hi>ſwearing?</hi> to the Devil of <hi>Sabboth-breaking,</hi> and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>prophaneſſe?</hi> That they might live and ſin without <hi>controul.</hi> Friends is this the <hi>turning</hi> that God looks for? Surely ſirs, theſe people (if they might have their wills) would bring in a <hi>night,</hi> a ſad and <hi>darke</hi> night in ſtead of a light and gladſome <hi>morning,</hi> a <hi>ſadder</hi> night then ever yet <hi>England</hi> ſaw; For if the Lord ſhould eſtabliſh <hi>us,</hi> and we make uſe of that eſtabliſhment to eſtabliſh <hi>our ſelves in ſin,</hi> and ſo provoke the Lord to go <hi>further</hi> from us, and leave us, we have juſt grounds to fear that the Lord would then <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come again amongſt us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Do theſe men turn unto the Lord? how many of them probably are in the <hi>Tavern</hi> at this time? how many in the <hi>Alehouſe</hi> at this very time? At <hi>this time</hi> I ſay, wherein (as one would expect) we
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119930:13"/> ſhould all <hi>as one man</hi> joyn together in our earneſt <hi>prayers,</hi> to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore a bleſſing from heaven upon the Counſel of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> ſhortly to be aſſembled, that the Lord would make them inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for our <hi>ſettlement</hi> and eſtabliſhment now after all our <hi>break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> and <hi>ſhakings.</hi> But <hi>where</hi> are they? Do theſe men walk in <hi>Gods</hi> wayes? Do theſe men look for a change that may be for the <hi>better?</hi> Do theſe men look for <hi>eſtabliſhment,</hi> and that the Nation ſhould be ſetled upon <hi>their</hi> deſires, and upon <hi>their</hi> endeavours?</p>
            <p>There is a place, that I hope in all things doth <hi>not run parallel,</hi> but in this is to our purpoſe. It is in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.19. <hi>All the people ſaid unto Samuel, pray for thy ſervants unto the Lord thy God, that we die not, for we have added unto all our ſins this evill to aske us a King.</hi> Now I ſay, I do not conceive that the Text runs parallel with our caſe <hi>in this particular;</hi> therefore miſtake me not. But now marke, <hi>Samuel ſaid unto the people, feare not, ye have done all this wickedneſſe; yet turn not aſide from following the Lord, but ſerve the Lord with all your hearts, and turn not aſide, for then ſhould you go after vaine things that cannot profit nor deliver, for they are vain.</hi> It was not ſo great a ſinne in them, but that <hi>deſiring</hi> and <hi>having</hi> a <hi>King</hi> was conſiſtent with <hi>ſerving the Lord:</hi> Nor had they thereby ſo <hi>ſin'd</hi> as to forſake God. <hi>Turn not aſide</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>from following the Lord, but ſerve the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. But then go on to the two laſt verſes: <hi>Onely feare the Lord and ſerve him in truth with all your heart, for conſider how great things he hath done for you: But if you ſtill do wickedly, you ſhall be conſumed both you and your King</hi>
            </p>
            <p>People think, Oh I if they had a <hi>King,</hi> all ſhall be well, their ſtate and condition ſhall then be <hi>proſperous,</hi> and they ſhall be all <hi>ſafe.</hi> But beloved, If men go after <hi>vaine</hi> things, if they do <hi>wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly,</hi> it cannot be a <hi>King</hi> that can help them. The people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> they had a <hi>King</hi> according to their deſires; But what, was that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to <hi>ſecure</hi> them? Surely if the <hi>Lord</hi> forſake them, it could not be their <hi>King</hi> that could help them: and therefore ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. <hi>The Lord will not forſake his people for his great names ſake, becauſe it hath pleaſed the Lord to make you his people.</hi> If the Lord hath once aſſumed a people to be his, he will <hi>do</hi> much for them, and <hi>beare</hi> long with them ere he will <hi>forſake</hi> them. And therefore as the Prophet there, <hi>verſ.</hi> 29. would <hi>pray for them, ſo alſo would he teach them the good and right way. Fear the Lord, ſaith he, and ſerve him in truth, with all your hearts, for conſider how great things he hath done for you,</hi> verſ. 24. And beloved, hath not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119930:13"/> 
               <hi>God</hi> done great things for <hi>us?</hi> What great <hi>hopes</hi> hath he given us of a <hi>ſettlement</hi> after all our <hi>feares</hi> and <hi>confuſions?</hi> And we expect a <hi>King:</hi> But <hi>if ye ſtill do wickedly, ye ſhall be deſtroyed both you and your King.</hi> Mark, That which the hearts of the people were <hi>ſet</hi> upon, was a <hi>King,</hi> nothing would <hi>pleaſe</hi> them but a <hi>King,</hi> yea you ſhall have a <hi>King;</hi> But yet <hi>do not go away from God, and follow after vain things,</hi> for if you do, <hi>you ſhall be conſumed</hi> and deſtroyed, <hi>both you and your King</hi> together. Beloved, there's nothing that ſo ſurely brings ruine and deſtruction upon a <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdome,</hi> as wilfull and <hi>reiterated</hi> ſins and wickedneſſes: <hi>If you ſtill do wickedly, you ſhall be deſtroyed both you and your King.</hi> You did wickedly <hi>before,</hi> and what became of your <hi>King?</hi> was it <hi>your</hi> wickedneſſe or <hi>his?</hi> Many of you will not ſay it was <hi>his.</hi> And if <hi>you ſtill</hi> do wickedly, the <hi>next</hi> King (for ought I know) may <hi>fare</hi> as he did, therefore take heed of <hi>ſin.</hi> Beloved, I propoſe this one thing to you, it was ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſin of the <hi>King</hi> (the Father) that brought the evill upon him, or the ſin of the <hi>People,</hi> or both together. If his <hi>own</hi> ſinne, then the judgement was juſt upon him as to <hi>God,</hi> though not <hi>in them who did it;</hi> But if it was the ſin of the <hi>people,</hi> let me ask you, will not that which ruin'd the <hi>Father</hi> ruine the <hi>Son? If you ſtill do wickedly, you ſhall be deſtroyed both you and your King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely <hi>Kings, Princes,</hi> and chief <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> are leaſt beholding to <hi>drunkards,</hi> to <hi>murderers,</hi> to <hi>prophane</hi> perſons, to unclean <hi>laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious</hi> perſons, to thoſe that <hi>wallow</hi> in the ſtinking puddle and naſty dunghill of <hi>ſin:</hi> Kings and Princes are leaſt of all beholding unto <hi>them,</hi> for they draw down judgement upon the whole <hi>Nation.</hi> Theſe perſons, though they look for a <hi>morning</hi> of joy and gladneſs upon the Nation, yet will ſurely bring a diſmal <hi>night</hi> of ſorrow notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their expectations.</p>
            <p>And therefore, <hi>Come let us return unto the Lord,</hi> that as <hi>he hath torn us for our</hi> ſins, ſo <hi>he may binde us up; and as he hath broken us</hi> for our tranſgreſſions, <hi>ſo he may heale us</hi> upon our returning: Here's <hi>incouragement,</hi> which is the ſecond part of the Text. Of which a little.</p>
            <p>Friends, none but he that <hi>ſmites</hi> us can <hi>beale</hi> us; none but he that <hi>tear's</hi> can <hi>binde</hi> us up. All other Phyſitians, all other Chyrurgions, they are but meer <hi>Quacks</hi> and <hi>Empericks.</hi> We may ſay of them as <hi>Job</hi> of his friends, <hi>Job</hi> 13.4. <hi>Ye are forgers of lies, ye are phyſitians of no value.</hi> And beloved, have we not found it ſo in our State-<hi>Mountebancks,</hi> who have ſet up their <hi>Stages,</hi> that they might pick
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119930:14"/> our <hi>Pockets,</hi> and made us bow <hi>down,</hi> that they might ride <hi>over</hi> us? Have we not found that of <hi>David</hi> verified? <hi>Men of high degree are a lie, and men of low degree are altogether vanity?</hi> Are they to be truſted in? Is there any more <hi>weight</hi> in them then in the <hi>duſt</hi> of the ballance? <hi>O let us return therefore unto the Lord, for he hath broken us, and he will heale us, he hath ſmitten us, and he onely can binde us up:</hi> He hath here promiſed it, if we return (as before) unto <hi>him:</hi> And beloved, conſider this, as God <hi>wounds</hi> and ſmites by his <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments,</hi> ſo he alſo <hi>heals</hi> and binds up by <hi>inſtruments.</hi> The enemies of Gods people, God makes uſe of as the rod in <hi>his hand</hi> to chaſtiſe and correct his Children for their <hi>ſins:</hi> and he alſo raiſes up <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> to deliver them from their <hi>ſufferings.</hi> In <hi>Eſay</hi> 58. there you have a promiſe made, that the juſt and righteous ſhall <hi>build the old waſte places, ſhall raiſe up the foundations of many generations, and ſhall be called the repairer of the breach, the reſtorer of the paths to dwell in.</hi> Do you look for happy dayes in <hi>England?</hi> Would you have the <hi>Old waſte places built,</hi> and the breaches repaired? Why, then ſee what the Lord requires of you: Read that place fore-quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.6. <hi>Is not this the Faſt that I have choſen?</hi> &amp;c. This is a day wherein you faſt and humble your ſelves to ſeek <hi>eſtabliſhment.</hi> Well, will you ſee what Faſt the Lord requires? <hi>Looſe the bands of wickedneſſe, undo every heavy burthen, let the oppreſſed go free, and that ye break every heavy yoke; It is to deale thy bread to the hungry, and that thou bring the poor that are caſt out to thy houſe; When thou ſeeſt the naked, that thou cover him, and that thou hide not thy ſelf from thine owne fleſh: Then ſhall thy light break forth as the morning, and thine health ſhall ſpring forth ſpeedily,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. <hi>They that be of thee ſhall build the old waſte places, thou ſhalt raiſe up the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of many generations,</hi> &amp;c. Though our government hath layn in the duſt theſe many <hi>yeares,</hi> and though we have had a dark and black <hi>night</hi> upon us, yet God can cauſe our <hi>light</hi> to break forth as the <hi>morning;</hi> he can raiſe us up ſome to <hi>build our waſte places,</hi> to be <hi>repairers of our breaches, and reſtorers of paths to dwell in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I ſay, the promiſe is to good and <hi>righteous</hi> men; Theſe are the men, <hi>if any,</hi> that muſt lay the <hi>foundations:</hi> not <hi>prophane</hi> looſe wretches, <hi>enemies</hi> to all righteouſneſſe, the Lord in mercy <hi>keep</hi> ſuch out of that great Aſſembly of <hi>Parliament:</hi> And if any get in, the Lord in his wiſdome find out a way to caſt them <hi>out</hi> again. Beloved, nothing but <hi>juſtice,</hi> and <hi>truth,</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> and <hi>mercy</hi> can heale a <hi>broken</hi> Nation, let us then this day, and every
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119930:14"/> day elſe beg of God, that he would graciouſly be pleaſed to be <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> with, and to ſit <hi>Preſident</hi> in, and over that great Councel of the Land, that they may <hi>break off every yoke, and take off every heavy burthen,</hi> and <hi>keep off</hi> all unjuſt yokes and heavy burthens that any whatſoever would impoſe upon us. That ſo that great Aſſembly may be a <hi>repairer</hi> of our breaches, and a <hi>reſtorer</hi> of our paths to dwell in. Let us pray that both they, and all we may be more carefull to bring King <hi>Jeſus</hi> into our <hi>hearts,</hi> then K. <hi>Charles</hi> into his <hi>Throne:</hi> Not as if I looked on theſe two as <hi>contradictory,</hi> oppoſite, or <hi>deſtructive</hi> the one unto the other; But thus, I tell you King <hi>Jeſus</hi> is to be <hi>preferred</hi> before any mortall creature what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever: And if he that ſhall rule be carefull to rule according to Truth, and under King <hi>Jeſus,</hi> If God and the great Council of the Nation ſhall think fit, <hi>Let him come and welcom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſirs, let me tell you, King <hi>Charles</hi> cannot ſave your ſoules; but if King <hi>Jeſus</hi> rule in your <hi>hearts,</hi> he can and will <hi>ſave</hi> you: What would it advantage you, if all of you had your hearts deſire <hi>here?</hi> If things go even as you would <hi>wiſh?</hi> and yet when <hi>Death</hi> comes, you ſhould be drag'd to <hi>Hell,</hi> to endleſſe <hi>torments,</hi> what would it advantage you? Be not then ſo mad as to purſue world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>concernments,</hi> or worldly <hi>comforts</hi> with ſuch eagerneſſe: But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all ſeek and purſue after things of <hi>everlaſting</hi> concernment: And I tell you no <hi>mortall</hi> King can ſave your ſouls, and therefore let us moſt look that King <hi>Jeſus</hi> his reign and government may be eſtabliſhed over us. See his ſweet and gracious government, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32. <hi>begin. Behold a King ſhall reign in righteouſneſſe, and Princes ſhall rule in judgement, and a man ſhall be as a hiding place from the winds, and a covert from the tempeſt as rivers of water in a dry land, &amp; as the ſhadow of a great rocke in a weary land,</hi> &amp;c. Ther's a deſcription given of a bleſſed and good King: He ſhall be a ſhelter, a cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he ſhall be <hi>all in all</hi> to a diſtreſſed people. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.5. there it is ſaid, <hi>Behold the dayes come ſaith the Lord, that I will raiſe unto David a righteous branch, and a King ſhal reign and proſper, and ſhall execute judgement and juſticein the earth; in thoſe days Judah ſhall be ſafe, and Iſrael ſhall dwell ſafely, and this is the name whereby he ſhall be called, The Lord our righteouſneſs.</hi> This is ſpoken of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, he that is the King of Kings, he ſhall rule in <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi> And he or they that <hi>Rule</hi> under him, muſt rule in <hi>Righteouſneſſe;</hi> Let us not then look ſo much (as moſt do) after <hi>wordly</hi> peace and freedome, and <hi>temporal</hi> deliverance from <hi>preſent</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:119930:15"/> burdens, as after <hi>ſpiritual</hi> peace, and freedome from <hi>everlaſting torments;</hi> not ſo much to enjoy <hi>periſhing</hi> comforts, as to have the <hi>comforts</hi> of everlaſting <hi>enjoyments:</hi> And then may we expect the performance of what is promiſed in the cloſe of our Text. <hi>After two dayes will he revive us, in the third day he will raiſe us up, and we ſhall live in his ſight;</hi> We ſhall live not onely <hi>temporally,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably and happy, but a life <hi>heavenly</hi> and everlaſting, we ſhall be happy to all <hi>eternity. Then</hi> (as it follows) <hi>ſhall we know, if we follow on to know the Lord,</hi> more of Gods minde, and of his <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> and he ſhall come unto <hi>us as the raine, as the early and latter rain upon the earth,</hi> which being parched with drought, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth it in <hi>readily,</hi> fructifieth, and bringeth forth <hi>abundantly. Come then, let us all return unto the Lord, for as he hath torne, ſo will he heale, and as he hath ſmitten, ſo will he bind us up.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="vindication">
            <p>HEre's my <hi>Sermon,</hi> now where's my <hi>ſin?</hi> What's my <hi>Charge</hi> with which I have been ſo (I cannot ſay whether more) <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly</hi> or <hi>maliciouſly</hi> traduced: why its three-fold; I have preacht againſt the <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>coming</hi> in of the <hi>King:</hi> So ſome, My whole Sermon drives at this; <hi>The coming in of the King would bring in prophaneneſſe;</hi> ſo others. A third ſort ſay, I am <hi>angry.</hi> Now to anſwer to theſe diſtinctly. And firſt, I have preacht againſt the <hi>King,</hi> and his coming <hi>in,</hi> I ask wherein? how doth that appear? I will come as cloſe and as ſpeedily as I can to my <hi>Charge,</hi> I mean to that part of my <hi>Sermon</hi> from whence they might <hi>ſuppoſe</hi> me crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous. I ſhall therefore paſſe over almoſt one halfe of it, for that was but by way of Explication: And it concern'd <hi>others, Iſrael.</hi> That troubles <hi>not,</hi> no preaching at a <hi>distance,</hi> and ſpeaking of <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> mens faults, and reproving <hi>them,</hi> that bites not, as much as you will of that: But this <hi>home</hi>-preaching, and treading <hi>too cloſe</hi> upon our heels, <hi>This</hi> gauls, <hi>this</hi> vexes <hi>this</hi> troubles us. Why, what's the matter? what's the matter? Did not you ſay. That becauſe by our <hi>ſins</hi> we had left <hi>God,</hi> therefore God had left <hi>us?</hi> And did you not ſay, That our <hi>Kings</hi> and our <hi>Princes</hi> heretofore, and our
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119930:15"/> 
               <hi>Princely</hi> Prieſts and <hi>Biſhops</hi> had been as <hi>ſnares upon Mizpah, and as nots upon Tabor</hi> (their high places and great offices). And how have they not rag'd and tyranniz'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And did you not beſeech us, that we ſhould not let the apprehenſions of our <hi>preſent greater ſufferings,</hi> cauſe us altogether to forget <hi>our former iniquities?</hi> And did you not adviſe us, that upon <hi>that</hi> day of our ſolemn Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein we ſought to God for <hi>ſettlement,</hi> that we ſhould not <hi>forget</hi> the cauſe and ground of our <hi>unſettlement?</hi> Here's enough to anſwer at once and together, and I think this is my <hi>greateſt</hi> charge. And now what of all this? Let me ask you by your <hi>cavilling</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this, Don't you diſcover your <hi>ignorance?</hi> Is it not plain you are not <hi>acquainted</hi> with the Scripture? Or that you take no <hi>notice,</hi> or <hi>underſtand</hi> not what you read, or hear? That you are meer <hi>ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> to the nature and manner of a <hi>true</hi> Faſt? Is not a <hi>faſting</hi> day (eſpecially publique, generall, and ſuch <hi>ſolemn</hi> Faſt dayes) a day wherein to humble our ſoules before the Lord by a <hi>hearty, ſincere,</hi> and <hi>impartiall</hi> confeſſion and acknowledgement of <hi>all</hi> our ſinnes? And being a <hi>generall</hi> day of Humiliation through the <hi>whole</hi> Land, to <hi>confeſſe</hi> and be humbled for the <hi>ſins</hi> of the whole Land in <hi>general.</hi> And in <hi>ſuch</hi> a day are not the ſins both of <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>People</hi> both <hi>paſt</hi> and <hi>preſent</hi> to be remembred and acknowledged? And that <hi>not onely</hi> in generall termes (which is moſtly ſlight and overly) but <hi>punctually</hi> and <hi>particularly,</hi> of thoſe ſins they were guilty of, and lay under. This is (if you know not, as it ſeems you do not) for your better information and (as I deſire) <hi>Reformation;</hi> Do but read the inſtances of the Solemn Faſts recorded in Scripture, and you will be <hi>wiſer</hi> hereafter. I reſer you for this more <hi>particularly</hi> to thoſe three moſt Solemn Faſts which are there recorded, <hi>Ezra</hi> 9. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9. and <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. And ſee and <hi>obſerve</hi> the manner of the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration, and whether their <hi>particular</hi> ſins were not <hi>enumerated,</hi> confeſſed and bewailed. And had we of this Land and Nation <hi>no</hi> ſins to be remembred? to be <hi>confeſſed?</hi> Are you <hi>ſo</hi> forgetfull? or were you <hi>ignorant</hi> of them? Are we not <hi>unſetled?</hi> Are not our <hi>foundations</hi> of government <hi>overturned?</hi> Do not the pillars of the Nation <hi>tremble?</hi> Is it not a <hi>Judgement?</hi> Do I not <hi>ſay</hi> ſo much? And what were there no <hi>ſins</hi> that are the <hi>cauſes</hi> of it? Do ſuch great, and heavy, and <hi>generall</hi> judgements befall a Nation (both <hi>King, Princes, Prieſts</hi> and <hi>People</hi>) without ſin <hi>procuring</hi> them? you dare not ſay ſo? And were there no ſins in <hi>England</hi> but the ſins of the <hi>people?</hi> What was the Popiſh <hi>Match?</hi> and the building of <hi>Houſes</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:119930:16"/> and <hi>Chappels</hi> thereupon for <hi>Idolatrous</hi> and ſuperſtitious worſhip? What was the countenancing and exerciſe of that falſe worſhip, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the Kings own dwelling? And were not our Communion-<hi>Tables</hi> turn'd into <hi>Altars,</hi> with ſuperſtitious <hi>cringings</hi> and <hi>bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> towards them? and in ſome places wax <hi>Tapers</hi> ſet upon thoſe <hi>Altars?</hi> and ſecond Service (which the people could not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>) there performed? How was the <hi>zealous</hi> profeſſion of Religion (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the nickname of <hi>Puritaniſme</hi>) diſcountenanced and diſgraced? How did the <hi>Court-Biſhops</hi> (eſpecially the Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Dr. <hi>Laud</hi>) vex, perplex, and ruine men in their <hi>High Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion Court,</hi> and <hi>Star-Chamber?</hi> How would <hi>drunken</hi> and <hi>prophane</hi> Miniſters (if but zealous for <hi>Ceremonies</hi>) give the <hi>checke</hi> to (and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the leaſt occaſion) <hi>trouble</hi> and ſue the <hi>beſt</hi> Knights and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the Country even for trifles, and be therein <hi>upheld</hi> and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced by thoſe Court-Biſhops; Inſomuch, that when the <hi>Knights</hi> and <hi>Gentlemen</hi> were aſſembled in <hi>Parliament,</hi> and had op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to be revenged <hi>upon</hi> them, they <hi>ding'd</hi> them <hi>quite</hi> down without mercy or conſideration.</p>
            <p>I need not tell you what courſes were taken that the <hi>King</hi> might be maintained without <hi>Parliaments,</hi> and ſo with out the <hi>love</hi> of his Subjects, and <hi>redneſſe</hi> of their grievances, I could name much, more; you that liv'd in thoſe times, and were able make <hi>obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> know it. If you don't, <hi>others</hi> do. And are not theſe grounds of <hi>unſettlement?</hi> And upon a <hi>ſpecial</hi> ſolemn Faſt (ſuch a one as <hi>this</hi> eſpecially) wherein we ſought to God for <hi>eſtabliſhment</hi> and <hi>ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>) would it not be proper, that theſe things and ſuch the like might and ſhould have been remembred and <hi>mentioned,</hi> the more to <hi>conſternate</hi> our ſpirits, and promote our <hi>humiliation:</hi> But you ſee I did not, I <hi>lightly</hi> paſt it over in <hi>Generals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh! But you ſaid, ſince thoſe three <hi>eminent</hi> perſons, profeſſors of thoſe three moſt noble Profeſſions, <hi>Divinity, Law,</hi> and <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke</hi> ſuffered upon the <hi>Pillory</hi> like Rogues and Cutpurſes in ſuch an <hi>opprobrious</hi> and diſgraceful manner. That the <hi>K.</hi> and his party never <hi>proſpered,</hi> did I ſay <hi>ſo?</hi> and did I not ſay <hi>true?</hi> Did not their Cauſe go every day backward? I ſay, <hi>their</hi> Cauſe, the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> for they I meant, I put them both together. There is a ſaying, <hi>In nomine Domini incipit omne malum:</hi> And every man that was acquainted with the <hi>Tranſactions</hi> of thoſe Times, cannot but acknowledge, that that was the <hi>ſource</hi> of all our <hi>miſeries:</hi> So dangerous a thing is it for <hi>Clergy-men</hi> to leave their Calling, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119930:16"/> turn <hi>Courtiers.</hi> Men whoſe riches lie in their <hi>heads,</hi> will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes <hi>tampering.</hi> 'Tis good therefore they be <hi>kept</hi> to their <hi>proper</hi> buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>For ſay, was it not a pretence of <hi>conformity</hi> and <hi>uniformity</hi> in <hi>Religion</hi> that began all our <hi>quarrell?</hi> Not that I think an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> an <hi>evil</hi> (what ever others ſay) but rather a <hi>good,</hi> and by all <hi>good</hi> wayes to be endeavoured, and I ſuppoſe till then we ſhall not be <hi>well</hi> ſetled: And ſure the <hi>quarrell</hi> began there, I could wiſh the <hi>ſettlement</hi> began there; For upon true judgement I ſpeak it, though it be a <hi>ſhame</hi> and a matter of ſadneſſe: Moſt of the troubles and combuſtions in <hi>Civil States</hi> have been either <hi>begun</hi> or <hi>fomented</hi> by men of our profeſſion, I mean of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and was it not ſo with us? Our <hi>firſt</hi> War intended, was it not againſt the <hi>Scots?</hi> and <hi>wherefore</hi> was it? who <hi>began</hi> it? Was it not called generally <hi>Bellum Epiſcopale,</hi> the <hi>Biſhops</hi> War, I put the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> together, with reſpect to <hi>this:</hi> The <hi>Biſhop</hi> could not begin a War (I mean arm the people) without a <hi>King.</hi> And the <hi>Biſhop</hi> having ſo great a power and <hi>influence</hi> upon the <hi>King,</hi> prevail'd with him to raiſe Armes againſt <hi>them</hi> (the Scots.) And the immediate <hi>Prodromus</hi> and forerunner of this <hi>War,</hi> was it not the moſt <hi>horrid</hi> and reproachful ſtanding of theſe eminent perſons upon the <hi>Pillory?</hi> I do profeſſe (the <hi>perſons,</hi> and every thing conſidered) it was the <hi>ſaddeſt</hi> ſight (next to the Kings <hi>beheading</hi>) that ever (eſpecially for many gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations) was ſeen in <hi>England.</hi> I ſaw not the <hi>latter,</hi> but I did the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi> And I well remember Mr. <hi>Burtons</hi> words when upon the <hi>Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lory; Marke it</hi> (ſays he) <hi>little do we know what this dry tree</hi> (point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Pillory) <hi>may bring forth.</hi> And <hi>ſpeedily</hi> after, the next news from <hi>Scotland</hi> was; <hi>If the Engliſhman looſe his lugg, the Scot would loſe his cragg,</hi> meaning againſt the rage and tyranny of the <hi>Biſhop:</hi> For having dealt thus <hi>barbarouſly</hi> with theſe three ſo <hi>emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent</hi> perſons, he then thought the <hi>terrour</hi> thereof would have <hi>daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> and cowed the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Nation, when as this did but <hi>heighten</hi> their indignation, and raiſe <hi>greater</hi> oppoſition againſt him.</p>
            <p>Yea, but were not the <hi>Scots</hi> too blame in this matter? It may be ſo, but I <hi>know</hi> it not, for I am not acquainted with the <hi>Laws, Rights,</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of their Kingdom, and therfore I ſay no more to it. But I ask this queſtion; Was their not entertaining <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and the <hi>Service-book a ſufficient</hi> ground to embroil <hi>two</hi> Nations, two <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Nations in <hi>War,</hi> to ſhed the <hi>blood</hi> one of another? And if (for <hi>conformities</hi> ſake with <hi>England</hi>) <hi>Scotland</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:119930:17"/> muſt have a <hi>Service-Book,</hi> why could not our own <hi>Engliſh Service-Book</hi> ſerve the turn? but there muſt be divers <hi>alterations,</hi> more conform to <hi>Romes</hi> language, then in our <hi>own Liturgie;</hi> of which Mr. <hi>Prins</hi> Book to that purpoſe can give you information. But the Scots abhorrid it as Swines fleſh, and it would not <hi>down</hi> with them. And no doubt, could <hi>they</hi> have been beaten into it, to have <hi>dined</hi> on it, <hi>we</hi> ſhould have been forced to have <hi>ſupt</hi> on it with them. But <hi>hereupon,</hi> on goes the <hi>War</hi> againſt them. And how well this <hi>Holy War</hi> was like to <hi>ſucceed,</hi> you may gueſs by the <hi>beginning;</hi> for even thoſe rude and ignorant Souldiers, who were led againſt the Scots, to <hi>kill</hi> them into <hi>conformity,</hi> in our <hi>own Countrey</hi> (as they paſt along towards <hi>Scotland</hi> (in deſpight of their Commanders) broke into divers <hi>Churches,</hi> pull'd down and burnt the <hi>rails</hi> about the Communion Table, and tore the <hi>Surplices,</hi> and the <hi>Common-Prayer Books:</hi> Theſe things were notorious, &amp; not done in a <hi>corner.</hi> It would be too much beyond my <hi>de ſign</hi> to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion all that followed: Plain it was, nothing proſpered <hi>after.</hi> And is this now ſuch a <hi>hainous</hi> offence to ſay ſo? Or was it not <hi>rather</hi> a matter to be <hi>acknowledged</hi> as a <hi>ſin,</hi> to be <hi>confeſt,</hi> and for which deeply to be <hi>humbled,</hi> and to repent of? I might have mentioned the cruel uſage of Dr. <hi>Layfield,</hi> who at the inſtigation of the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop,</hi> after a <hi>long</hi> impriſonment in the Fleet, was whipt from thence to <hi>Weſtminiſter,</hi> where raw (as he was) he ſtood upon the <hi>Pillory,</hi> his noſtrils <hi>ſlit,</hi> and burnt in the <hi>cheeks</hi> or <hi>forehead.</hi> But did I charge this evil, or any other, upon the <hi>King,</hi> as the cauſe either of <hi>his</hi> or <hi>our</hi> ſuffering? Nay, did I not <hi>diſclaim</hi> that bold preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, in the words even immediately foregoing, ſaying, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's ſins were greater (ours, or our Princes) God the Judge beſt knows: For what am I, that I ſhould ſtep into his chair.</hi> This I <hi>concluded</hi> on, and I think none can <hi>deny</hi> it, If our <hi>ſins</hi> had not been <hi>univerſal,</hi> the <hi>judgement</hi> would not have been ſo <hi>general?</hi> And I do profeſs, I dare not judge the <hi>Kings</hi> ſins to be <hi>greater</hi> then the <hi>peoples,</hi> becauſe he drank <hi>deeper</hi> in the <hi>judgement:</hi> But if I <hi>had</hi> charged the ſin of the <hi>King</hi> upon himſelf, or his <hi>Father,</hi> why ſhould theſe men pretend to be ſo angry? it would not have been to <hi>reproach</hi> him, or triumph over him, but to have been <hi>humbled</hi> with him, and <hi>for</hi> him (as well as for our ſelves) for our <hi>pardon,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation and amendment: So that I hope this is not to ſpeak againſt the <hi>King,</hi> or his coming <hi>in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I ſuppoſe, they will not <hi>ſhew themſelves</hi> (my <hi>Reproachers,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:119930:17"/> I mean) ſo <hi>ignorant</hi> or <hi>ſottiſh</hi> as to ſay, That I ſpake againſt the <hi>King</hi> (or his coming <hi>in</hi>) by telling them, that their <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> might be a means to <hi>deſtroy</hi> both him and them: For which I quoted that place, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.19. and ſo on: Much leſs, did I ſpeak againſt the <hi>King,</hi> in adviſing them to be more <hi>careful</hi> to bring King <hi>Jeſus</hi> into their hearts, then King <hi>Charls</hi> to the <hi>Throne;</hi> and telling them, That they may be <hi>undone with him, yea, and by him, both temporally and eternally: But that King Jeſus will aſſuredly ſave them, if he rule over them.</hi> I hope you will not ſay this is a crime? if you do, the <hi>Lord</hi> make you <hi>wiſer.</hi> And this I think is all you have to <hi>charge</hi> me with in this matter; and how <hi>wiſely, juſtly, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably, Chriſtianly,</hi> let all wiſe men <hi>judge.</hi> Confident I am, what I <hi>delivered,</hi> might have been ſpoken even in the Kings <hi>preſence,</hi> and he would not have been <hi>offended:</hi> What would theſe <hi>captious</hi> hearers have ſaid, had I uſed ſuch <hi>plain</hi> language as was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto him at his <hi>Coronation,</hi> in the Coronation <hi>Sermon?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coronation Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preacht at <hi>Scoon, Ian.</hi> 1651. by Mr. <hi>Rob. Douglas.</hi> Printed at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berdeen,</hi> 1660.</note> That his <hi>Father</hi> ſet himſelf in a <hi>hoſtile</hi> way, to overthrow <hi>Religion, Parliaments, Laws,</hi> and <hi>Liberties;</hi> and in <hi>page</hi> 27. of the ſame Sermon, they charge his Grandfather King <hi>James</hi> with <hi>foul defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> and that he <hi>pereſecuted</hi> faithful Miniſters, and that he laid the <hi>foundation</hi> whereupon his Son (<hi>our late King</hi> (ſays he) did build <hi>much miſchief to Religion, all the days of his life.</hi> And he tells him, that the guiltineſs of the tranſgreſſion <hi>lies</hi> upon the <hi>Throne</hi> and <hi>Family;</hi> and that is one of the ſins for which <hi>he</hi> had profeſſed humiliation very lately, and adviſes him to take <hi>warning.</hi> And in his Exhortation to the <hi>King,</hi> page 32. he tells him, There is <hi>too much</hi> iniquity upon the <hi>Throne</hi> by his Predeceſſors, <hi>who framed miſchief by a Law:</hi> ſuch Laws as have been <hi>deſtructive to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, grievous to Gods people.</hi> and <hi>page</hi> 36. he may ſay it freely, That <hi>chief cauſe</hi> of the judgement upon the <hi>Kings Houſe,</hi> hath been <hi>his Grandfathers breach of Covenant with God; and his Fathers following his ſteps, in oppoſing the work of God, and his Kirk, within theſe Kingdoms.</hi> He ſays, <hi>They have broken the Covenant with God, and men have broken Covenant with them.</hi> Moſt cruelly and perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly (ſays he) they have invaded the Royal Family, and trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den upon all Princely Dignity: And therefore charges him <hi>in Chriſts name,</hi> not to break Covenant; if he do, he aſſures him, <hi>The Controverſie is not ended between God and his Family,</hi> but it will be carried on to <hi>further</hi> weakning <hi>if not to the utter overthrow of it.</hi> Here's <hi>plain</hi> dealing, now what would our men have ſaid to <hi>this</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:119930:18"/> matter? Surely never a villain in <hi>England</hi> would have preached <hi>ſuch</hi> a Sermon: and yet ſuch fooliſh <hi>ſots</hi> have we in <hi>England,</hi> to ſay ſo of a Sermon that hath <hi>none</hi> of all this (nor any thing <hi>like</hi>) in it.</p>
            <p>But now Sirs, to convince you of your <hi>perverſeneſs,</hi> and to let you ſee, how like you are to thoſe noxious creatures (the <hi>Flies</hi>) that <hi>flie-blow</hi> wholſome meat, ſo are you. It is uſuall with them, if there be any <hi>bruiſed</hi> place, they are ſure to light upon that <hi>firſt,</hi> and there to <hi>ſucke</hi> and <hi>feed</hi> themſelves: But if there be <hi>none,</hi> they <hi>flie-blow</hi> ſo long, till they have made it <hi>fit</hi> for their purpoſe: So do you <hi>flie-blow</hi> diſcourſes. For whereas you charge me to be <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> and his coming <hi>in,</hi> did I not ſay, <hi>It was a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that we were removed from our ancient foundations?</hi> And what could I mean, or did I mean? But the <hi>changing our government.</hi> And did I not quote that place, <hi>Iſay</hi> 3. to the end of <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. as a <hi>dreadfull judgement</hi> moſt ſadly fallen upon us? And did I not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ſay; That as we had been under <hi>that curſe and judgement,</hi> ſo we might ſee that <hi>bleſſed morning</hi> promiſed to Gods people, in the ſame Prophet, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>ver.</hi> 25, 26, 27. Do but read the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and let any man ſay what could be thence intended? And did I not pray <hi>for the haſtning of that happy morning?</hi> And when I quoted that place in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.19. to the end, did I not in <hi>expreſs words ſay,</hi> That that place <hi>in all things did not run parallel</hi> with our condition? But that in <hi>ſomething</hi> it was pertinent to my <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe;</hi> which was in the later part <hi>onely,</hi> in that the peoples <hi>wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs would deſtroy themſelves, the King, and Kingdome?</hi> And did I not in <hi>plain words</hi> ſay, That that portion of Scripture held not pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallell <hi>in that very particular,</hi> in that it was ſaid <hi>they ſin'd in deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a King?</hi> with more to that purpoſe, as you may ſee in the Sermon. And did I not ſay, That <hi>if it were the late Kings own ſins,</hi> (which I did not, nor dare I determine) <hi>that brought that judgment upon him, it was not juſt in them who did it.</hi> And when I adviſed you to be more careful <hi>to bring King Jeſus into your hearts; then King</hi> Charles <hi>into the Throne,</hi> did I not expreſly, and in theſe ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant words ſay; <hi>That the one was not oppoſite, contradictory, or deſtructive to the other?</hi> But onely that King <hi>Jeſus</hi> was to be <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd</hi> before him? And that if he (King <hi>Charles</hi>) be minded to rule <hi>for</hi> him, and <hi>under</hi> him; did I not ſay, <hi>If God and the great Council ſee it fit, let him come and welcome?</hi> Well, the Lord <hi>forgive</hi> you, and make you <hi>wiſer,</hi> and more diſcreet and boneſt. And I cannot
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119930:18"/> paſſe by, but muſt reprove you for one moſt <hi>abominable lie</hi> of ſome of you; That I ſhould pray in my Prayer, That as the Lord had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered us from <hi>one</hi> Devill, ſo he would deliver us from <hi>another;</hi> and that <hi>hereby</hi> I did mean the <hi>King.</hi> Good Lord! what a lying <hi>malicious</hi> Devill hath poſſeſt theſe people. No, theſe and ſuch like <hi>prophane</hi> and <hi>ungodly</hi> wretches in an <hi>humane</hi> ſhape are the <hi>Devils</hi> I prayed againſt. I prayd, <hi>That as the Lord had graciouſly in a good meaſure delivered us from the devil of Herſie and blaſphemie, ſo that he would alſo keep us and deliver us from the Devil of prophaneneſſe:</hi> And the <hi>God</hi> to whom I prayed knows, that theſe <hi>ungodly</hi> wretches are all the <hi>Devils</hi> I prayed againſt, and <hi>no other;</hi> not having any <hi>thought,</hi> apprehenſion, or <hi>imagination</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> in this particular. And ſo much to my <hi>firſt</hi> charge.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Now for my <hi>ſecond,</hi> in which I ſhall be brief. My Sermon, ſay ſome, drove all at <hi>this, The bringing in of the King would bring in all prophaneſſe;</hi> But did I any where ſay ſo? Truly I needed not, Prophaneſſe is in <hi>already</hi> in the Nation; nor did I <hi>thinke</hi> the King would bring it <hi>in,</hi> and I hope he <hi>never</hi> will. But this I think, all the <hi>ungodly</hi> and <hi>prophane</hi> people in the <hi>Nation</hi> have a very great and ſtrong deſire of the <hi>Kings</hi> coming in, as hoping to have as much <hi>liberty</hi> to be <hi>prophane,</hi> and to exerciſe it, as they had <hi>before.</hi> Oh! how hath the <hi>Parliament Acts</hi> and Ordinances hampered and chained, and <hi>fettered</hi> theſe beaſts; They cannot <hi>ſwear,</hi> or be <hi>drunk</hi> but they muſt <hi>pay</hi> for't. Taverns, Innes, and Ale-houſe muſt be ſhut on the Lords day, <hi>all day long,</hi> that they cannot tipple, &amp; be drunk. They muſt not <hi>walke</hi> in the <hi>ſtreets</hi> nor in the <hi>fields</hi> on that day under a penalty, and many of them have been <hi>ſued</hi> and <hi>indicted</hi> for it, and the like. And oh! How like wilde <hi>Buls</hi> in a net, have they <hi>fretted,</hi> and <hi>vext,</hi> and <hi>raved</hi> at it? Oh! that <hi>bleſſed</hi> book (think they) that moſt <hi>excellent</hi> book for <hi>ſports</hi> on the <hi>Sabboth;</hi> That was a <hi>good,</hi> a <hi>bleſſed,</hi> a <hi>merry</hi> time with us. Theſe people are like thoſe, <hi>Jer.</hi> 44.16,17,18. <hi>As for the word that thou haſt ſpoken unto us in the name of the Lord, we will not hearken unto thee: But we will certainly do whatſoever thing goeth forth out of our own mouth, to burn incenſe unto the Queen of heaven, and to pour out drink-offerings unto her, as we have done, we and our fathers, our Kings and our princes in the Cities of Iudah, and ſtreets of Ieruſalem: For then had we plenty of victuals, and were well, and ſaw no evill. But ſince we left off to burn incenſe to the queen of heaven,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>we have wanted all things, and have been conſumed by the ſword, and by the famine.</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:119930:19"/> Well ſirs, think as you will; For my part I thinke that <hi>accurſed</hi> book was none of the leaſt <hi>provocations</hi> that drew down the <hi>judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of God upon the <hi>Nation.</hi> And yet how glad would many be of this <hi>licentious</hi> liberty re-introduced: And oh! for ſome good <hi>Court Biſhops</hi> to help us in this particular againſt the <hi>Round-heads,</hi> and theſe puritanical <hi>Presbyterians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beloved Reader, I charge this upon the <hi>Court Biſhops</hi> onely; For <hi>confident</hi> I am, there were many <hi>good</hi> and godly <hi>Biſhops</hi> in the Nation who abhorred that <hi>execrable thing,</hi> and yet this is the thing theſe miſerable wretches <hi>look</hi> for. And here let me not be <hi>miſtaken,</hi> or <hi>miſ-reported,</hi> as if I thought that <hi>none</hi> but prophane and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe perſons <hi>look</hi> and <hi>long</hi> for the <hi>Kings</hi> coming. No, far be it from <hi>my</hi> ſoul; For I am <hi>aſſured</hi> there are many <hi>godly</hi> and <hi>honeſt</hi> hearts, ſober and <hi>diſcreet</hi> perſons who earneſtly <hi>deſire</hi> it, and would be glad to <hi>ſee</hi> it, But as for <hi>prophane</hi> and <hi>ungodly</hi> perſons, (<hi>drunkards ſwearers, whoremongers, Sabboth-breakers, deſpiſers</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>godlineſſe</hi> in the <hi>power</hi> of it) upon what good account can <hi>they</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire him, I leave it to any <hi>reaſonable</hi> man to judge. Do they deſire it either for the <hi>Kings</hi> good, or their <hi>own</hi> good, certainly <hi>no?</hi> But they are <hi>ſure,</hi> if one <hi>party</hi> (whom they how hate) ſhould <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail,</hi> they ſhall ſtill walke in their <hi>chains</hi> and <hi>fetters;</hi> but from <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other</hi> they hope (at leaſt) for <hi>freedome.</hi> And ſhould they be <hi>ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered</hi> and reſtrained by that <hi>other,</hi> they would hate both <hi>alike.</hi> For 'tis not <hi>this</hi> perſon or <hi>that</hi> perſon, <hi>this</hi> party or <hi>that,</hi> which is the <hi>quarrel</hi> or offence. But the old <hi>enmity</hi> of oppoſition and hatred between the two <hi>ſeeds</hi> of <hi>godly</hi> and <hi>ungodly.</hi> And if the <hi>King</hi> be, as by ſome he is reported, (which God grant) <hi>godly,</hi> and ſhall <hi>ſhew</hi> it by his <hi>curbing</hi> their <hi>wickedneſſe,</hi> they will not <hi>like</hi> him <hi>long,</hi> but would be <hi>weary</hi> of him. And clearly the obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and information of their <hi>prophaneſſe</hi> the laſt Faſt day, is to me (yea, and to any conſidering perſon) a ſufficient argument of their <hi>ungodlineſſe:</hi> and theſe <hi>onely</hi> are the men I ſpoke of, and deſired to conſider the <hi>vanity</hi> of their <hi>expectations.</hi> That (if it had been the will of God) I might have been inſtrumental to <hi>undeceive</hi> but ſome <hi>one</hi> of them, and ſee how they <hi>requite</hi> me for my labour! But I ſhall not <hi>loſe</hi> it.</p>
            <p>And truly, although theſe be the perſons I <hi>chiefly</hi> aym at (as moſt <hi>worthy</hi> of reprehenſion: Yet ſince I am now diſcharging my <hi>conſcience</hi> in this way (of writing) which I think not to do <hi>again.</hi> I would beg leave to <hi>adviſe</hi> ſome of our more civill and <hi>moderate</hi> op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponents
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119930:19"/> in <hi>one</hi> particular. 'Tis too eaſie and <hi>familiar</hi> with many of you (upon the <hi>leaſt</hi> provocation, ſometimes <hi>without</hi> it) to return upon us, with the word <hi>Presbyterian</hi> by way of <hi>reproach</hi> as a <hi>Nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name,</hi> and to inveigh againſt <hi>Presbytery:</hi> But Sirs, do you <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand</hi> what you do? It's true, the <hi>Biſhops</hi> have a <hi>long</hi> time kept the <hi>name</hi> (and thing) in a kind of <hi>ſilence</hi> under <hi>hatches.</hi> But will you (without <hi>paſſion</hi> and <hi>partiality,</hi> and as in the preſence of <hi>God</hi> (for ſo I deſire to deale with you) be <hi>informed</hi> in the truth? Then I muſt tell you this <hi>one</hi> thing, the Scripture ſpeaks more <hi>of,</hi> and <hi>for</hi> Presbyters then <hi>Biſhops</hi> Not that I bring this as an <hi>argument</hi> to prove <hi>Presbytery</hi> to be more ſacred then <hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> For I thinke them both ſo <hi>alike,</hi> and I intend not to handle that <hi>controverſie.</hi> My deſigne is, to let you know (if the <hi>Scripture</hi> may rule you) you may as well ſpeak <hi>ſcornfully</hi> of <hi>Biſhops</hi> as <hi>Presbyters;</hi> and of <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy,</hi> as of <hi>Presbytery;</hi> For I tell you again, the Scripture makes <hi>oftner</hi> mention of <hi>Presbyters</hi> then <hi>Biſhops.</hi> Now for your <hi>informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and to <hi>clear</hi> this to you, you muſt know, that the word <hi>preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter</hi> (though we by <hi>uſe</hi> make it <hi>Engliſh</hi>) is a <hi>Greek</hi> word, which we in our Engliſh <hi>Bibles</hi> have always tranſlated by the word <hi>Elder.</hi> It comes from <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Senex,</hi> one that's <hi>old.</hi> And <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior,</hi> one that's <hi>Elder.</hi> And this word is uſed in Scripture ſometimes in a <hi>naturall</hi> ſenſe, to ſignifie one elder in <hi>age:</hi> and ſometimes in an <hi>eccleſiaſtical</hi> ſenſe, for an <hi>Officer</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> of Chriſt. Now it was my purpoſe to have examined all the places in the <hi>Greek</hi> Teſtament where the word <hi>Presbyter</hi> is uſed, and to have obſerved how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times it was uſed in an <hi>eccleſiastical</hi> ſence, ſignifying a <hi>Church-Officer:</hi> But the day before the writing hereof, there came very <hi>happily</hi> to my hand a Book lately publiſhed by one, <hi>whoſe other workes praiſe him in the gate,</hi> and <hi>this</hi> not a little, <hi>ſcil.</hi> Mr. <hi>George Lawſon, Politica Sacra,</hi> which ſaves me ſome labour, which I am willing to embrace at this time for <hi>haſt</hi>-ſake, eſpecially from <hi>ſuch</hi> an Author. And he tells me <hi>page</hi> 139. of that Book, that he finds the word <hi>Presbyter</hi> in an <hi>eccleſiastical</hi> ſence and notion about <hi>ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen</hi> times in the <hi>New</hi> Teſtament. And now as for the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is ſometimes tranſlated an <hi>Overſeer</hi> (as <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28.) and ſometimes a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> I could quickly number them, for 'tis but <hi>five</hi> times uſed: and one of them is ſpoken not of an <hi>ordinary</hi> Church-officer, but of our Lord <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.25.</p>
            <p>So that I ſay the Scripture makes more <hi>uſe,</hi> and more <hi>often</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the word <hi>Presbyter</hi> then <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and therefore not ſo to be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119930:20"/> 
               <hi>ſlighted</hi> and <hi>reproached,</hi> or to be uſed as a terme of <hi>diſgrace</hi> to any man, unleſſe you have a mind to <hi>diſgrace</hi> the Scripture which thus honours <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Presbyterians</hi> above <hi>Biſhoips.</hi> Yea, but Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops <hi>are</hi> above them; How know you that? They <hi>were</hi> ſo, and ſo <hi>have</hi> a long time; that's true. But did the Scripture put them there? Good ſirs let no man be <hi>angry</hi> with me, if I expreſs my mind <hi>freely.</hi> I mean not to make a <hi>quarrel</hi> of it, nor contend with any man <hi>about</hi> it, for I have better work to do; then <hi>nodum in ſcirpo quaerere.</hi> But where doth the Scripture put a <hi>Biſhop</hi> above a <hi>Presbyter?</hi> Let any man in the world ſhew me the place, Shall I ask you <hi>one</hi> thing? According to the <hi>uſuall</hi> apprehenſion, and among us in <hi>England,</hi> what was the <hi>office</hi> and <hi>buſineſſe</hi> of a <hi>Biſhop?</hi> And what is the <hi>office</hi> and <hi>buſineſs</hi> of a <hi>Preſbyter?</hi> You'l ſay, the <hi>office</hi> of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> was to <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>govern,</hi> for ſo they <hi>did.</hi> And the <hi>office</hi> of a <hi>Preſbyter</hi> or <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> is to <hi>teach</hi> and feed the Flock. But now, doth the Scripture thus <hi>diſtinguiſh</hi> and put a <hi>difference?</hi> No, but if there be <hi>any</hi> to be found there, 'tis on the <hi>other</hi> ſide the leaf, That puts the honour of <hi>ruling</hi> upon the <hi>Preſbyters</hi> (the Elders) and the buſineſſe of <hi>tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching</hi> and <hi>feeding</hi> upon the Overſeers, the Biſhops. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. <hi>The Elders</hi> (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Presbyters) <hi>that rule well are worthy of double honour.</hi> And the Apoſtle in <hi>Acts</hi> 20. puts the buſineſſe of <hi>feeding</hi> (one part whereof is teaching) upon <hi>Biſhops.</hi> For <hi>verſ.</hi> 28. <hi>Take heed</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>unto your ſelves, and to all the flocke over which the holy Ghoſt hath made you</hi> (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>Biſhops</hi> (ſo in the Greek) <hi>to feed the Church of God.</hi> See here, you are made <hi>Biſhops</hi> to <hi>feed. El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> to <hi>rule,</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> to <hi>feed.</hi> So that by this it ſeems in the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> times the <hi>Biſhop</hi> was not the <hi>better</hi> man. But beloved, are you willing to know the <hi>truth?</hi> and wil you not <hi>kick</hi> againſt it, when 'tis laid <hi>plainly</hi> before you? Why then know, that <hi>then</hi> (in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles time) <hi>Preſbyter</hi> and <hi>Biſhop</hi> were all <hi>one.</hi> And that (as the before-commended Mr. <hi>Lawſon</hi> hath it) <hi>whatſoever ſome of late have ſaid to the contrary, Presbyter and Biſhop were onely two different words, ſignifying the ſame Officer.</hi> And for evidence <hi>undenyable,</hi> do but read the 17. verſe of that Chapter (<hi>Acts</hi> 20.) and there you ſhall <hi>finde</hi> who thoſe perſons <hi>are</hi> whom he calls <hi>Biſhops</hi> or <hi>Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers,</hi> even the <hi>Preſbyters</hi> (the Elders) of the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> put both together, and it runs <hi>clearly</hi> thus. St. <hi>Paul ſaid to the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters</hi> (or Elders) <hi>of the Church of Epheſus, Feed the flocke of God, over which the holy Ghoſt hath made you Biſhops.</hi> I wonder why our laſt Tranſlators of the Bible did not render it (<hi>Biſhop</hi>) here, but
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119930:20"/> 
               <hi>[Overſeer]</hi> which they have <hi>not</hi> done in any other place where this word is uſed. But I know the <hi>myſterie,</hi> and I could give you <hi>ſome</hi> account, as I have been credibly informed.</p>
            <p>But to be ſhort, compare 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1,2,3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with <hi>Titus</hi> 1.5,6,7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and you ſhall finde the <hi>qualifications</hi> of a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and of an <hi>Elder</hi> (or Presbyter) to be the <hi>ſame.</hi> And in that place to <hi>Titus,</hi> if you compare in 5. verſe and the 7th. you ſhall finde the Apoſtle uſing <hi>Elder</hi> and <hi>Biſhop</hi> as <hi>ſynonimous,</hi> ſignifying the <hi>ſame.</hi> This is plain, the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelves were not the onely <hi>Biſhops</hi> even in the Apoſtles <hi>times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to cloſe all in <hi>this</hi> particular, let that place 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning be conſidered, where St. <hi>Peter</hi> writing to the ſeverall <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> (as appears <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.1.) in that 5th. Chap. he exhorts the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters</hi> (or Eldrs) to a faithfull diſcharge of their <hi>duty</hi> (which is a diligent <hi>feeding</hi> their Flock, <hi>without</hi> lording it over them) much <hi>leſſe</hi> over their fellow Elders, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2, 3. of which he profeſſes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be one in <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. <hi>The Elders</hi> (or Presbyters, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>which are among you, I exhort, who am</hi> (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>alſo a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter (or Elder)</hi> a fellow-Presbyter, or a <hi>Presbyter</hi> together with you <hi>Feed the flock of God which is among you, taking the overſight thereof,</hi> ſo we read it; but in the Greek it is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, playing the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> or doing the work or buſineſſe of <hi>Biſhops.</hi> So that <hi>then,</hi> Biſhop and Presbyter, both <hi>name</hi> and <hi>thing, Title</hi> and <hi>employment</hi> was all <hi>one,</hi> without any <hi>domination</hi> according to the rule and Canon of their <hi>Lord</hi> and Maſter, <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.42. where a requeſt having been made in the behalf of ſome of his Diſciples for <hi>domination,</hi> he calls them to him, and ſayes, <hi>Ye know that they which are accounted to rule over Gentiles</hi> (or Heathens) <hi>exerciſe Lordſhip over them, and their great ones exerciſe authority upon them: But ſo it ſhall not be among you,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Much more <hi>might</hi> be ſaid, and <hi>is</hi> ſaid by others in this matter. And if any deſire <hi>further</hi> information &amp; <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> herein, let them (without prejudice) read Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> five Diſputations of <hi>Church-government</hi> and <hi>worſhip,</hi> and there they ſhall finde theſe things <hi>plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and truly ſtated and diſcuſſed.</p>
            <p>What then (will ſome ſay) you would have all <hi>leveld</hi> and <hi>equal.</hi> And you would have every <hi>Miniſter</hi> (every Presbyter) a <hi>Pope,</hi> to domineer and <hi>Lord</hi> it in his own <hi>Pariſh?</hi> Friends, be not <hi>too</hi> haſty, I do not ſay ſo, nor would I <hi>have</hi> it ſo. I would not have all <hi>equall,</hi> all are not fit for every thing. I am not of their <hi>opinion</hi> who ſay, <hi>all</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:119930:21"/> things requiſite to government and diſcipline in the <hi>Church</hi> are <hi>fully</hi> contained (I mean <hi>punctually</hi> and particularly) in <hi>Scripture.</hi> Nor do thoſe who <hi>ſay</hi> ſo, make it good in their <hi>practice,</hi> nor <hi>can</hi> they. And I ſay <hi>further;</hi> That <hi>opinion</hi> hath been the mother and nurſe of much <hi>ſchiſme</hi> and <hi>faction,</hi> I grant that much here muſt be left to <hi>prudence,</hi> and that not of <hi>ſingle</hi> or particular <hi>Paſtors, Preſbyters,</hi> or <hi>Biſhops;</hi> but to the conſideration and determination of the moſt <hi>godly, learned,</hi> grave, and able in the <hi>Nation,</hi> to which I would have <hi>all</hi> to <hi>conform.</hi> If any like it not, they are at their liberty. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> and order is more <hi>precious,</hi> then to be <hi>deſtroyed</hi> for the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of <hi>ſuch</hi> as will never be ſatisfied, as not <hi>well</hi> knowing their <hi>owne</hi> mindes. And as for <hi>Lordly</hi> dominion, and <hi>Poping</hi> it in our <hi>Pariſhes,</hi> I do profeſſe I do <hi>abhor</hi> it under <hi>every</hi> form. I as much adhominate a <hi>lording</hi> Presbyter, as a <hi>lording</hi> Biſhop; no name, ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, or <hi>pretext</hi> whatſoever gives us any <hi>ſuch</hi> authority: And I would <hi>begge</hi> (as I do deſire) that we might be kept to <hi>that</hi> which ſhall appear to be our <hi>proper</hi> buſineſſe; which if thoſe of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion <hi>had</hi> been, <hi>England</hi> had not been in ſo <hi>ſad</hi> a condition as it is this day. I like not the Scotch <hi>Stool of Repentance,</hi> nor would I have excommunicate perſons <hi>driven</hi> into the <hi>Church</hi> again by the <hi>ſecular</hi> power: As by Writs <hi>de excommunicato capiendo,</hi> or the like. It may force men to an <hi>hypocritical</hi> acknowledgment of ſome <hi>kinde</hi> of penitence, but it cannot produce <hi>true</hi> repentance. I would have <hi>Church</hi>-cenſures, reach no <hi>further,</hi> nor cut any <hi>deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> then their <hi>ſpiritual</hi> ſword will penetrate. I approve not <hi>rigid</hi> compulſions by the arme of <hi>fleſh,</hi> in ſuch things which are the <hi>onely</hi> work of the <hi>ſpirit;</hi> as is true and <hi>unfeigned</hi> repentance. Of which, if people by <hi>conſtraint</hi> make a feigned <hi>profeſſion,</hi> it doth but <hi>harden</hi> them in their ſin, and make them <hi>impudent;</hi> which (as I have been credibly informed) is <hi>too</hi> manifeſt in <hi>ſome</hi> places of the <hi>world,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the <hi>ſtrictneſſe</hi> of their <hi>diſcipline.</hi> I would have <hi>Church</hi> affairs (in this reſpect) ſo <hi>managed,</hi> as if the <hi>Civil</hi> Magiſtrate were no <hi>friend</hi> to Religion, farther then that thoſe who <hi>profeſſe</hi> it, and live <hi>peaceably,</hi> may be <hi>protected</hi> by him from <hi>outward</hi> violence.</p>
            <p>No, let the beauty, <hi>excellency,</hi> benefit and <hi>neceſſity</hi> of the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> of the Church, with the <hi>priviledges</hi> thereof be clearly layd open to the people. Let the <hi>hazard,</hi> danger, and miſchief of <hi>juſt excommunication</hi> be declared and urged upon them. And let all Chriſtians <hi>with draw</hi> all countenance and <hi>unneceſſary</hi> leſſowſhip and ſociety <hi>from</hi> them, according to the Scriptures. <hi>And</hi> if the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119930:21"/> 
               <hi>ſenſe,</hi> ſhame, and grief <hi>thereof</hi> (with other ſuch conſiderations, (ſet on by the ſpirit of <hi>God</hi>) will not <hi>humble</hi> them: <hi>Let them alone till the Lord cometh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then, I would not have <hi>thoſe</hi> who are by <hi>juſt</hi> excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation caſt out of <hi>one</hi> Church or Congregation, received <hi>in</hi> into <hi>another,</hi> for this were the way to make <hi>Conventicles</hi> of Hereticks, <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> blaſphemers, and all manner of <hi>prophane</hi> and ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ones: And in this I conceive the <hi>Civill</hi> Magiſtrate is <hi>much</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd (eſpecially being a <hi>Chriſtian</hi>) For 'tis found <hi>too</hi> true by ſad experience, that <hi>factions</hi> in the Church beget <hi>fractions</hi> in the State. And therefore my ſoul longs for ſuch a <hi>happy</hi> day, wherein by the favourable <hi>aſpect</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Magiſtrates, all wayes of <hi>faction, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration</hi> and <hi>diviſion</hi> may be fore-cluded: And if men be <hi>otherwiſe</hi> minded, let them ſit <hi>ſtill</hi> and be quiet. Or if they will be <hi>doing,</hi> it were good if they would go and <hi>gather</hi> Churches among the <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,</hi> and not <hi>intrude</hi> themſelves into other mens labours.</p>
            <p>This which I have now declared, was and is <hi>onely</hi> to allay the <hi>heat</hi> of thoſe mens <hi>ſtomacks,</hi> who (being <hi>altogether</hi> ignorant of what the <hi>Scripture</hi> hath and ſaith in the behalf of <hi>Preſbyters</hi> and Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans) do ſo <hi>ſlight</hi> and <hi>vilifie</hi> them, as to make the <hi>name</hi> and thing a <hi>reproach</hi> unto them. You may as well call a man <hi>prick-eard</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, as <hi>prick-ear'd</hi> Presbyterian: And I have done this to give you <hi>timely</hi> warning, and to <hi>prevent</hi> your prophaneſſe. If you will not <hi>leave</hi> it, know, however you <hi>ſcorn</hi> them, the Scripture <hi>honours</hi> them; and take heed of <hi>kicking againſt the pricks:</hi> Your <hi>prophaneſſe</hi> is that I complain <hi>of,</hi> and if you <hi>will</hi> go on, <hi>Dominus venit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I have <hi>one</hi> thing <hi>more</hi> to ſpeak to, and then <hi>manum de tabula;</hi> and it is to <hi>fore-warn</hi> (or rather <hi>after-warn</hi> you (for it hath been <hi>too</hi> long practiſed) of <hi>another</hi> evill: and that is, reproaching <hi>zealous,</hi> home and plain, down-right <hi>preaching,</hi> with the odious names of <hi>paſſion, anger,</hi> and <hi>railing.</hi> And let me tell you, this is no other then Sathans <hi>ſubtlety</hi> to render <hi>our</hi> preaching unto you <hi>unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable,</hi> and ineffectual. We <hi>confeſs</hi> we are <hi>men</hi> ſubject to <hi>paſſion</hi> (yea and <hi>ſinfull</hi> paſſion) as <hi>others</hi> are.<note place="margin">Iam. 5.17.</note> Inſtances might be given from <hi>Scripture</hi> of the Lords moſt <hi>precious</hi> Saints and ſervants in this <hi>ſad</hi> particular. But what then? Is <hi>plain</hi> and home, and down-right <hi>preaching</hi> paſſion and <hi>railing?</hi> Take heed of that. Nay, is it not <hi>lawful</hi> ſometimes to be angry and in <hi>paſſion?</hi> Eph. 4.26. <hi>Be angry and ſin not.</hi> A man may be <hi>angry,</hi> and not <hi>ſin.</hi> Nay, 'tis a <hi>ſin</hi> not to be angry <hi>ſometimes.</hi> Is not the Lord <hi>himſelfe</hi> ſaid ſometimes to be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119930:22"/> 
               <hi>angry?</hi> And can <hi>he</hi> ſin? It's true, St. <hi>Paul</hi> would not have a <hi>Biſhop</hi> (or <hi>Preſbyter</hi>) <hi>ſoon angry;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1.7.</note> not <hi>ſuddenly, lightly, haſtily.</hi> But doth <hi>that</hi> infer he ſhould not be angry at <hi>all?</hi> Nay rather, doth it not infer the <hi>contrary?</hi> He <hi>may,</hi> he <hi>muſt</hi> be ſometimes <hi>angry?</hi> Would you be <hi>drunke,</hi> and <hi>ſwear,</hi> and <hi>curſe,</hi> and <hi>prophane Gods Sabboths,</hi> and <hi>hate</hi> and ſcorn <hi>ſtrict</hi> profeſſion of <hi>Religion,</hi> and openly <hi>declare</hi> your enmity, and <hi>ſhall</hi> not (<hi>muſt</hi> not) we be <hi>angry?</hi> Muſt we not <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove you ſharply,</hi> cuttingly? So the word properly ſignifies (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) I'le tell you ſirs, That which you call <hi>anger,</hi> and <hi>paſſion,</hi> and <hi>railing,</hi> is in <hi>Scripture</hi> call'd <hi>zeale.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1.13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I could be <hi>large</hi> in this particular: but there is ſo <hi>much</hi> in this kind done to my hand <hi>already</hi> by a worthy and reverend brother, and that in <hi>print,</hi> in a little book, called <hi>Elias Abatement,</hi> or <hi>Corruption in the Saints;</hi> Being a <hi>Sermon</hi> preached by Mr. <hi>Thomas Caſe</hi> at the Funerals of a godly Miniſter, (one Mr. <hi>Gualter Roſwel</hi>) I ſay this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo <hi>excellently</hi> and fully done to my hand, I ſhall forbear the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proſecution from my <hi>own</hi> thoughts. Onely becauſe every one hath not that Book; and ſome may meet with <hi>this,</hi> who poſſibly may never meet with <hi>that:</hi> And for that <hi>prejudice</hi> againſt <hi>Miniſters</hi> upon <hi>this</hi> account, is ſo <hi>great</hi> a miſchief to <hi>them,</hi> eſpecially to their <hi>people</hi> (being as I ſaid) a device of <hi>Sathan</hi> to hinder the entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their <hi>Doctrine</hi>) I ſhall take ſo much <hi>pains</hi> as to lay before you <hi>ſome</hi> of that which that Reverend Author <hi>hath</hi> to this purpoſe, and which he did in <hi>vindication</hi> of that <hi>deceaſed</hi> brother, who it ſeems was <hi>changed</hi> to be a man <hi>paſſionate</hi> and <hi>cholerick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt place he confeſſes; he was a man in whom the black a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſt humour of <hi>choler</hi> had predominance in his natural conſtitution, (and who can help that?) And he ſayes, that many times gave a <hi>tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture</hi> to his diſcourſe and actions; which ſtanders by, more <hi>cenſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> then <hi>candid,</hi> interpreted to his <hi>unjuſt prejudice.</hi> Then he gives him a <hi>high</hi> commendation for his <hi>eminent</hi> gifts, parts, and abilities, comparing him (in his meaſure) to <hi>Elias,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> in <hi>many</hi> things. Amongſt <hi>others</hi> he ſays his Miniſtery was a <hi>thundring Miniſtery:</hi> and I would to God (ſayes he) we had <hi>more</hi> of them, there is <hi>need</hi> of them. And becauſe tis ſo good and pertinent, take <hi>more.</hi> Thunder (ſays he) purgeth the air: And if ſo, we have need of <hi>more</hi> ſuch ſons of Thunder amongſt us, and not ſuch as will ſing <hi>Placentia</hi> unto people: Sow <hi>pillows</hi> under their elbows, and ſing men to Hell with ſweet <hi>Lullabies</hi> of <hi>peace, peace,</hi> when there is no peace. Our air is peſtilentiouſly infectious in the ſenſe of our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119930:22"/> Phyſitians, and our Climate is mortally infected with the peſts of <hi>hereſies</hi> and <hi>blaſphemies,</hi> and with the <hi>putrid</hi> ſtench of all manner of poyſonous luſts, which is the fatall ſource of all our plagues both in Church and State: and this our precious brother (ſaith he) was <hi>deeply</hi> ſenſible of: And hence it was that his ſpirit was <hi>warmed</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him to a more then <hi>ordinary</hi> degree of zeal in his Miniſtery.</p>
            <p>And he ſays his <hi>courage</hi> was rival with his <hi>zeal,</hi> he feared not the face of any man, but would <hi>boldly</hi> reprove (as <hi>Elias</hi>) even the <hi>high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt.</hi> In all the Changes that went over his head, in all the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies of the times, wherein he exerciſed his Miniſtry, he was a moſt ſtrenuous aſſertor of the Truth, and a moſt couragious oppoſer of <hi>errour</hi> and <hi>innoviation:</hi> and that even, while ſome higher then others by head and ſhoulders (in their own eyes) did baſely and <hi>unworthily</hi> betray their cauſe, he feared not the face of <hi>man,</hi> in the cauſe of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt:</hi> He durſt tell the <hi>greateſt</hi> perſon he had to do with of their faults, upon <hi>juſt</hi> occaſion in the worſt of Times. He was a hammer to beat down error and blaſphemy, where-ever it met him. He could not bear with them that preacht down <hi>Paedobaptiſme,</hi> the <hi>Chriſtian Sabboth,</hi> Univerſities, Schools of Learning, <hi>Ordination,</hi> and other ordinances and inſtitutions of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.3.</note> as it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied, that ſome would not endure <hi>ſound</hi> Doctrine, ſo he would not endure <hi>unſound</hi> Doctrine. He ſayes, he could not bear with <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers,</hi> nor <hi>they</hi> with him, ſo that by this means he became a man of <hi>contention.</hi> And yet he commends him for a man of a <hi>tender</hi> ſpirit, <hi>mortified</hi> to the world, free and liberall, much in faſting and prayer.</p>
            <p>And yet he ſayes, he had his ſhare in the <hi>perſecution</hi> of the Times wherein he lived, from his very <hi>firſt</hi> entrance upon his <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> according to the propheſie of our <hi>Saviour, Mat.</hi> 5.11,12. And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſays he, It had been a <hi>wonder</hi> if he ſhould have <hi>eſcap't</hi> it. For (as our Lord ſubjoyns the reaſon to his prediction of the Apoſtles ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, <hi>ver.</hi> 13.) his Miniſtry was <hi>ſalt.</hi> He was ſalt in his <hi>life,</hi> and <hi>ſalt</hi> in his doctrine: Not onely <hi>ſavoury,</hi> but <hi>quicke</hi> and <hi>corroding,</hi> ſmart and ſearching, which corrupt times, and ulcer'd conſciences could not bear, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3.</p>
            <p>And this ſays he <hi>inrag'd &amp; inflam'd the ſpirits of unſound men,</hi> and raiſed much trouble and perſecution againſt him, <hi>whereſoever</hi> he came, which occaſioned him <hi>often to flit from one place to another,</hi> to avoid the fury of <hi>unreaſonable</hi> men. And he ſayes, other of Gods ſaithful Miniſters have had their <hi>ſhare</hi> with him in <hi>this</hi> kind of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119930:23"/> 
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.23. The world cannot bear the plain-dealing of Goſpel-Miniſters. None ſo <hi>hated</hi> as the <hi>reprover in the gate, Amos</hi> 5.10. They hate him that rebuketh in the gate, and they abhor him that ſpeaketh uprightly.</p>
            <p>And now, as to the thing it ſelf (which <hi>ſome</hi> call anger and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but indeed is <hi>zeal</hi> and faithfulneſs) I cannot leave till I give you in, what this <hi>Reverend</hi> man hath to that purpoſe, and it's hugely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable and advantagious. He aſſerts, That <hi>the affection of anger rightely qualified, and managed, is of ſingular uſe and advantage in the life and worke of a Chriſtian, eſpecially of a Miniſter of the Goſpel;</hi> which ought in no wiſe to be branded with the <hi>uſual</hi> ſcandal of <hi>cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> and <hi>paſſion.</hi> They are his words all.</p>
            <p>I make no queſtion (ſayes he) the falſe prophets, and their ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced proſelytes, ſtuck not to blaſt the holy Prophet (he means <hi>Elias</hi>) in my Text, with the ſame reproach, <hi>a furious man,</hi> a man of an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate</hi> and <hi>unbridled ſpirit,</hi> that valued not mens lives, but in his anger would not ſtick to call downe fire from heaven to deſtroy an <hi>hundred men at a time,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But ſaith he, let me mind you of this in the general. The <hi>paſſion of anger,</hi> with other affections in nature, at what time the perſon in whom they are is <hi>regenerate,</hi> they do <hi>change</hi> their nature, &amp; become <hi>regenerate too.</hi> And being baptized with the blood and ſpirit of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, they receive divine <hi>impreſſions,</hi> and ſo paſſe into the cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of <hi>gracious affections</hi> and <hi>diſpoſitions,</hi> and become inſtruments of exceeding honour and ſervice in the hand of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who is pleaſed to make uſe of them in his own work.</p>
            <p>And then inſtances in <hi>divers;</hi> and among the reſt, <hi>Paſſion</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>born again of water and the ſpirit, becometh the grace of zeale, and holy jealouſie for God, and for the intereſt of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anger</hi> ſanctified is that to the affections, which <hi>edge</hi> is to the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument,</hi> which <hi>varniſh</hi> is to <hi>colours,</hi> which <hi>winde</hi> is to the <hi>ſails</hi> of a Ship. Judgement is the <hi>ballaſt,</hi> but <hi>zeal</hi> is the full gale. It is as <hi>met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> to the <hi>horſe.</hi> It is the <hi>activity</hi> of every grace, every affection <hi>red hot</hi> for Jeſus Chriſt, which <hi>much water cannot quench, neither can the floods drown it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 8.7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, <hi>Paſſion refined</hi> and <hi>ſpiritualiz'd,</hi> is every faculty of the ſoul, acting to <hi>its height</hi> for the glory of God.<note place="margin">Pſal. 69.9.</note> 
               <hi>The zeal of thy houſe hath eaten me up.</hi> To be ſhort; <hi>Sanctified anger</hi> in the Saints of God, is not that which the world takes it to be, a <hi>ſhort madneſs,</hi> but a <hi>grace</hi> of the ſpirit of God. Yea, it is a <hi>compound</hi> and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119930:23"/> 
               <hi>temperament</hi> of all graces, acting in <hi>ſummo gradu,</hi> in the height of intention for the promoting of the concernments of Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>I told you before, that <hi>Elias</hi> was a uſeful man, <hi>though</hi> he was <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> to <hi>paſſion.</hi> I ſhall tell you more now: He was <hi>therefore ſo uſefull,</hi> BECAUSE <hi>he was ſubject to paſſion.</hi> His anger and paſſion being ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, <hi>made</hi> him ſo abundantly active for God, and the reformation of the <hi>publique worſhip, doctrine,</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> in his generation. Had he wanted his <hi>paſsion,</hi> he had wanted ſome of his <hi>zeal</hi> for God.</p>
            <p>And ſo was it (ſays he) with our worthy brother deceaſed; That which an idle, wanton, looſe, luke-warm generation of <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> as well as <hi>prophane</hi> perſons (for the palliating of their own hypocriſie, and <hi>Gallio-like</hi> indifferency in matters of Religion) called <hi>paſsion</hi> and <hi>choler</hi> in him, was indeed and in truth nothing but his <hi>zeal</hi> and <hi>courage,</hi> and <hi>activity</hi> for Jeſus Chriſt, which truly did even <hi>conſume</hi> him.</p>
            <p>Alas! In this apoſtate generation, all things have loſt their proper names. The <hi>Devil</hi> appears in <hi>Samuels mantle,</hi> Satan in the form of an <hi>Angel of light:</hi> And <hi>ſin</hi> puts on the habit of <hi>vertue,</hi> that it may deceive the more ſafely.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>lukewarmneſs</hi> and curſed <hi>neutrality</hi> in Religion paſſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad for <hi>meekneſs</hi> and <hi>ſweetneſs of ſpirit. Carnal policy</hi> for Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>prudence. Curſed compliance</hi> with the luſts of men, for <hi>moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and command of a mans ſpirit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>While <hi>zeal</hi> and <hi>fidelity</hi> to the Truth, ordinances and government of Jeſus Chriſt, hear ill in the world, and ſuffer all the <hi>odium</hi> and ſcandal that a reviling world, and the venemous wit of malice can heap upon it. Truly <hi>the earth is not able to bear their words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus this reverend and worthy man, for whoſe pains herein I thank him, and thank God for him, and for his <hi>providence</hi> that brought this piece to my hand, at a time ſo <hi>ſeaſonable;</hi> as I do <hi>alſo</hi> for the work of that worthy and ingenuous <hi>Dr.</hi> to whom I owe ſo much for my <hi>Preface.</hi> In matters of <hi>this</hi> nature, which are of <hi>proper</hi> concernment, it is better to deal by <hi>others</hi> words, then our <hi>own.</hi> For by this it will appear we are not <hi>alone</hi> in our judgement and manner of <hi>procedure,</hi> in diſcharge of our duty, nor in <hi>ſuffering</hi> for it.</p>
            <p>There is <hi>one</hi> exception <hi>more</hi> which ſome make againſt my <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,</hi> which is, It was <hi>unſeaſonable.</hi> And to this I briefly anſwer: It's plain, theſe perſons who urge this, are not acquainted with the <hi>Topicks,</hi> and proper ſeats of arguments, <hi>deliberative,</hi> or <hi>perſwaſive.</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:119930:24"/> I did, and do conceive that if I might be ſo <hi>free</hi> as to make uſe of the <hi>reſpects</hi> of the people to the <hi>King</hi> at <hi>any</hi> time, and from <hi>thence</hi> to dehort them <hi>from</hi> ſin, and to perſwade them to <hi>turn to the Lord,</hi> that <hi>ſo</hi> both King and people may be (by Gods bleſſing) <hi>ſetled</hi> and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed upon ſure foundations; That now was the <hi>onely</hi> time I will not ſay, but ſurely in all good reaſon it was a very <hi>ſeaſonable</hi> time: When people are <hi>high,</hi> and full, &amp; earneſt, and that <hi>generally,</hi> and it being almoſt the <hi>onely</hi> talk of <hi>bringing in the King;</hi> was it not <hi>ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable</hi> upon a ſolemn <hi>Faſting</hi> day, to minde people of being <hi>more carefull of bringing King Jeſus into their hearts, then any mortal King unto the Throne?</hi> And inaſmuch as <hi>ſin</hi> (the ſins of the <hi>people,</hi> (for that way I carried it) had deſtroyd our <hi>former</hi> King, that <hi>therefore</hi> they ſhould beware, leſt by <hi>their</hi> ſinnes they deſtroy the <hi>latter.</hi> Had I ſaid any thing by way of <hi>oppoſition,</hi> or had I not very <hi>frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> upon all occaſions (and that not in corners onely, but <hi>openly</hi>) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd my judgement for the <hi>coming in</hi> of the King, it had been ſomething: But ſurely theſe men have ſome <hi>prejudice</hi> againſt my perſon: But whether they have or no, thus much I tell them (in the fore quoted words of the reverend Dr. in the Preface, and where this exception is in part anſwered) <hi>I will no more learn of them how to preach, then they will learn of me to buy and ſell.</hi> And ſo I leave them.</p>
            <p>And now upon the <hi>whole</hi> matter, I will draw towards a cloſe with this <hi>requeſt</hi> to thoſe who may be <hi>Auditors</hi> hereafter, that they would not, by <hi>ignorant</hi> or wilfull miſtakes, or if reports, make the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of <hi>Miniſters</hi> a means to <hi>repair</hi> their decayd and broken <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes,</hi> in taking <hi>up,</hi> or carrying <hi>on,</hi> and telling <hi>lies</hi> to thoſe whom they have a mind to <hi>ingratiate</hi> themſelves withal, and may (as they hope) lift them <hi>up</hi> out of their <hi>low</hi> condition.</p>
            <p>I muſt tell you ſirs in few words (for I have gone beyond what I intended already) in thus <hi>doing</hi> (belying and reproaching the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel) you do but the <hi>Devils</hi> buſineſs. Satans greateſt deſign is to hinder the progreſs of the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> And he well knows, <hi>contempt of the Miniſter brings neglict of his Doctrine</hi> It is a truth ſo clear in your own experiences, that I need not ſay more to it: And conſider you are hereby <hi>injurious</hi> not onely unto <hi>us</hi> (weakning our hands that we cannot reap the deſired fruit of our labours) But you injure both your <hi>ſelves</hi> and <hi>others</hi> of our people, who by your <hi>evill</hi> practice and example in this kind are drawn into the <hi>prejudice,</hi> ſin and miſchief with you. I ſhut up all with this: If it be an <hi>honour,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:119930:24"/> which brings a great <hi>reward</hi> with it, to be inſtrumentall in the work of mens <hi>ſalvation;</hi> what can they expect who in any kind <hi>hinder</hi> it? Conſider it <hi>betimes,</hi> and be wiſe for the <hi>future.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="vindication_of_author">
            <p>TO fill up the void place of my paper, I thought good to add a teſtimony or two conducent to my purpoſe in the preceding <hi>Vindication,</hi> and that from a witneſſe not to be ſuſpected of <hi>partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> in this matter; And that is Dr. <hi>Laud, Archbiſhop</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> taken out of his own <hi>Diary</hi> or Day book of every days obſervations under his <hi>own</hi> hand, and found with him by Mr. <hi>Pryn,</hi> when he ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched him and his Lodgings in the <hi>Tower.</hi> And this I have in a Book publiſhed by Mr. <hi>Pryn,</hi> intituled, <hi>A breviate of the Life of</hi> William Laud, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where <hi>page</hi> 21. you have this paſſage recorded.</p>
            <p>June 14. <hi>This day</hi> John Baſtwick, <hi>Dr of Phyſicke,</hi> Henry Burton <hi>Batchellor of Divinity, and</hi> Will: Pryn <hi>Barreſter at Law, were cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for Libels againſt the Hierarchy of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>June 26. <hi>The ſpeech I then ſpake in the Star-Chamber, was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the King to be Printed, and it came out</hi> June 25. I ſuppoſe the firſt <hi>June</hi> 26. ſhould have been <hi>June</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>And this now manifeſtly evidences, their <hi>ſufferings</hi> were not for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny offence againſt the <hi>Civill</hi> State: And what power that <hi>Biſhop</hi> then had to <hi>tyrannize,</hi> and how they did <hi>rage</hi> for things of their <hi>proper</hi> concernment.</p>
            <p>And what was the cauſe of the tumults in <hi>Scotland</hi> (which we all know led in the tumults in <hi>England</hi>) the ſame <hi>Biſhop</hi> (who beſt knew it) will tell you. In the ſame page, thus.</p>
            <p>April 29 1638. <hi>The tumults in</hi> Scotland <hi>about the Service-Book, offered to be brought in, began</hi> July 23. 1637. <hi>And continued increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by fits, and hath now brought that Kingdom in danger; No que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion there is a great concurrence between them, and the Puritan party in</hi> England, <hi>a great aym there to deſtroy me in the Kings opinion,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Mark here. Theſe 3. men ſuffered in <hi>June</hi> 37. and the Tumults began the <hi>next</hi> moneth following, and ſo went onwards: And did they proſper?</p>
            <p>And he here acknowledges <hi>theſe tumults began about the Service-Book:</hi> Which what a one it was, and how differing from ours, you may read in <hi>another</hi> Book of Mr. <hi>Pryns,</hi> entituled, <hi>Hidden works of darkneſs brought to light,</hi> diſcovering the practices uſed to <hi>uſher Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery</hi> into our Realms.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:119930:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>I'le add one teſtimony more out of the former Book, <hi>page</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>Thurſday, Decemb. 5. <hi>The KING declared his reſolution for a Parliament, in caſe of the Scottiſh Rebellion: The firſt movers to it were my Lord Deputy of</hi> Ireland, <hi>my Lord Marqueſs</hi> Hamilton, <hi>and my ſelfe: And a Reſolution voted at the Board to aſsiſt the King in extraordinary wayes, if the Parliament ſhould prove peeviſh, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">By the Board, he means the Councel-Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Obſerve here now, who, and why, and whence came all our Troubles. And how <hi>per fas, aut nefas,</hi> it muſt be carried on (as it was) to <hi>his,</hi> the <hi>Kings,</hi> and the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> undoing: And ſee, if the <hi>Parliament</hi> anſwer not their ends, in this good <hi>Biſhops</hi> language, they are <hi>peeviſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:119930:25"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
